<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Get Things Done]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>site-lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Get Things Done</title><link/></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 03:12:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="site-lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 03:12:02 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[2.5_1650 - Bradstreet, Anne - Poemas]]></title><description><![CDATA[---tab Resumen
Aquí va el texto principal de la nota.
Puedes usar **negritas**, *cursivas* y [[enlaces]]. ---tab To My Dear and Loving Husband
# Análisis: To My Dear and Loving Husband
**Autora:** [[Anne Bradstreet]]
**Año:** c. 1650 (Publicado póstumamente en esta forma en 1678)
**Forma:** Distísticos heroicos (Heroic Couplets) - *Iambic Pentameter* --- ## 📖 1. Vocabulario Histórico y Arcaico
El poema utiliza un inglés del siglo XVII (Early Modern English). Aquí están los términos clave para entender el texto original: * **Thee / Thy:** Pronombre singular para "tú" y "tu" (objeto y posesivo). * *Contexto:* Su uso aquí denota intimidad y cercanía, reservado para Dios o familia muy cercana.
* **Ye:** Pronombre plural para "vosotras" o "ustedes". * *Contexto:* *"Compare with me, ye women"* (Comparen conmigo, mujeres). Se dirige a todas las demás mujeres del mundo.
* **Doth:** Forma arcaica de "does" (tercera persona singular). * *Contexto:* *"The East doth hold"* (Que el Este posee/tiene).
* **Ought:** En este contexto, es una variante ortográfica de **"Aught"**, que significa "cualquier cosa" o "algo". * *Contexto:* *"Nor ought but love..."* (Ni nada excepto amor...).
* **Manifold:** En gran número, abundantemente, multiplicado. * *Contexto:* *"Reward thee manifold"* (Te recompense con creces).
* **Persever:** Forma arcaica de "Persevere" (perseverar). * *Nota de pronunciación:* En la época de Bradstreet, se acentuaba en la segunda sílaba (*per-SEV-er*), por lo que rimaba perfectamente con "ever". --- ## 🔍 2. Análisis de Metáforas e Imágenes ### A. La Unidad Matrimonial ("If ever two were one...")
&gt; *"If ever two were one, then surely we."*
* **Referencia Bíblica:** Alude a Mateo 19:6 ("y los dos serán una sola carne").
* **Significado:** Establece la unión espiritual y física completa. No son dos individuos separados, sino una entidad única. Es una afirmación audaz de armonía perfecta. ### B. Valor Material vs. Valor Espiritual ("Mines of gold...")
&gt; *"I prize thy love more than whole mines of gold / Or all the riches that the East doth hold."*
* **La Metáfora:** Compara el amor con la riqueza comercial más codiciada del siglo XVII.
* **Contexto Histórico:** "The East" (Las Indias Orientales) era la fuente de especias, seda y oro. Era el símbolo máximo de riqueza exótica y material.
* **Significado:** Bradstreet rechaza el materialismo. La riqueza del Nuevo Mundo o del Viejo Mundo no tiene valor comparada con su esposo. ### C. La Sed y el Fuego ("Rivers cannot quench")
&gt; *"My love is such that rivers cannot quench"*
* **La Imagen:** El amor se presenta como un fuego tan intenso o una sed tan grande que ni todos los ríos pueden apagarlo o saciarla.
* **Referencia:** Posible alusión al Cantar de los Cantares (Song of Solomon 8:7): *"Las muchas aguas no podrán apagar el amor, ni lo ahogarán los ríos"*. Esto eleva su amor terrenal a un nivel casi sagrado. ### D. La Economía del Amor ("Repay", "Recompense")
Bradstreet utiliza términos **financieros** para describir sus sentimientos:
* *"Prize"* (Valorar/Tasar)
* *"Recompense"* (Recompensar/Pagar)
* *"Repay"* (Repagar/Devolver deuda)
* **Análisis:** Ella siente que el amor de su esposo es tan inmenso que ella está en "deuda". Como no tiene "capital" emocional suficiente para pagarle (porque él le da demasiado), pide a los cielos ("The heavens") que salden la deuda por ella ("reward thee manifold"). --- ## ⚖️ 3. La Paradoja Final (El cierre)
&gt; *"That when we live no more, we may live ever."* Este es un cierre clásico puritano que resuelve la tensión entre amar el mundo y amar a Dios.
1. **La contradicción aparente:** ¿Cómo podemos vivir si ya no vivimos?
2. **La solución cristiana:** Si se aman fielmente en la Tierra (siguiendo el mandato divino), serán recompensados con la **Vida Eterna** en el cielo.
3. **Conclusión:** La muerte no es el final del amor, sino la puerta hacia su eternidad. --- ## 💡 Notas para la clase
* **Tono:** A diferencia del estereotipo puritano (austero, frío), este poema es **apasionado, confidente y sensual**.
* **Estructura:** Observar el uso de **Anáfora** en las primeras tres líneas ("If ever... If ever... If ever...") que construye un argumento lógico creciente. ---tab Imágenes
![[mi-imagen.png]]Anne Bradstreet (1612–1672) es una de las figuras más importantes de la literatura colonial temprana y es reconocida históricamente como la primera persona (hombre o mujer) en ser publicada como poeta en las colonias británicas de Norteamérica.
<img alt="Anne Bradstreet.png" src="images/anne-bradstreet.png" target="_self">
Origen: Nació en Inglaterra en una familia culta y acomodada. Recibió una educación muy superior a la de la mayoría de las mujeres de su época. <br>Migración: En 1630, a los 18 años, emigró a América a bordo del barco Arbella como parte de la gran migración puritana a la <a data-href="Colonia de la Bahía de Massachusetts" href="colonia-de-la-bahía-de-massachusetts.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Colonia de la Bahía de Massachusetts</a>. Estatus: Tanto su padre (Thomas Dudley) como su esposo (Simon Bradstreet) fueron gobernadores de la colonia, lo que la situaba en la élite social, aunque esto no la eximió de las durezas de la vida pionera (enfermedades, incendios, riesgos de parto). El hito: Su libro, The Tenth Muse Lately Sprung Up in America (1650), fue publicado en Londres (supuestamente por su cuñado y sin su conocimiento previo). Fue un éxito inmediato en el Viejo Mundo. Dos voces: Pública/Formal: Sus primeros poemas eran largos, históricos y filosóficos, diseñados para demostrar que una mujer podía tener intelecto y razón.
<br>Privada/Íntima: Los poemas (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="2.5_1650 - Bradstreet, Anne - Poemas > ^tee2au" data-href="2.5_1650 - Bradstreet, Anne - Poemas#^tee2au" href="2.5_1650-bradstreet,-anne-poemas.html#^tee2au" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">To My Dear and Loving Husband</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="2.5_1650 - Bradstreet, Anne - Poemas > ^j3uqn3" data-href="2.5_1650 - Bradstreet, Anne - Poemas#^j3uqn3" href="2.5_1650-bradstreet,-anne-poemas.html#^j3uqn3" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">In Reference to her Children</a>) pertenecen a su etapa más madura y personal. Son considerados hoy en día su mejor trabajo porque rompen con el estereotipo puritano frío y muestran emociones humanas profundas, miedo a la muerte y amor apasionado. Al leer los textos que transcribiste, notarás estos temas recurrentes:
El amor matrimonial: En contra de la creencia popular de que los puritanos rechazaban la pasión, Bradstreet describe un amor profundo, físico y espiritual hacia su esposo ("If ever two were one, then surely we"). La maternidad y la ansiedad: Dado que la mortalidad era alta, muchos de sus poemas (como Before the Birth of One of Her Children) son testamentos o despedidas anticipadas, mostrando la ansiedad real de morir en el parto o de perder a sus hijos. Fe vs. Apego Terrenal: Existe una tensión constante en su obra. Como puritana, debía centrarse en Dios y el cielo, pero sus poemas revelan lo mucho que amaba el mundo, a su esposo y a sus hijos ("birds"), y lo difícil que le resultaba la idea de soltarlos. Bradstreet es fundamental porque nos da una ventana única a la vida doméstica femenina del siglo XVII. No escribe solo sobre teología, sino sobre el miedo a que su casa se incendie, el dolor de que sus hijos se vayan de casa y el amor romántico, humanizando una época histórica que a menudo vemos como rígida y distante.By Anne BradstreetIf ever two were one, then surely we.
If ever man were loved by wife, then thee.
If ever wife was happy in a man,
Compare with me, ye women, if you can.
I prize thy love more than whole mines of gold,
Or all the riches that the East doth hold.
My love is such that rivers cannot quench,
Nor ought but love from thee give recompense.
Thy love is such I can no way repay;
The heavens reward thee manifold, I pray.
Then while we live, in love let’s so persever,
That when we live no more, we may live ever. Source: The Complete Works of Anne Bradstreet (1981)
Subjects: Living, Marriage &amp; Companionship, Love, Romantic Love, RelationshipsBy Anne BradstreetAll things within this fading world hath end,
Adversity doth still our joyes attend;
No ties so strong, no friends so dear and sweet,
But with death’s parting blow is sure to meet.
The sentence past is most irrevocable,
A common thing, yet oh inevitable.
How soon, my Dear, death may my steps attend,
How soon’t may be thy Lot to lose thy friend,
We are both ignorant, yet love bids me
These farewell lines to recommend to thee,
That when that knot’s untied that made us one,
I may seem thine, who in effect am none.
And if I see not half my dayes that’s due,
What nature would, God grant to yours and you;
The many faults that well you know I have
Let be interr’d in my oblivious grave;
If any worth or virtue were in me,
Let that live freshly in thy memory
And when thou feel’st no grief, as I no harms,
Yet love thy dead, who long lay in thine arms.
And when thy loss shall be repaid with gains
Look to my little babes, my dear remains.
And if thou love thyself, or loved’st me,
These o protect from step Dames injury.
And if chance to thine eyes shall bring this verse,
With some sad sighs honour my absent Herse;
And kiss this paper for thy loves dear sake,
Who with salt tears this last Farewel did take.By Anne BradstreetI had eight birds hatcht in one nest,
Four Cocks were there, and Hens the rest.
I nurst them up with pain and care,
No cost nor labour did I spare
Till at the last they felt their wing,
Mounted the Trees and learned to sing.
Chief of the Brood then took his flight
To Regions far and left me quite.
My mournful chirps I after send
Till he return, or I do end.
Leave not thy nest, thy Dame and Sire,
Fly back and sing amidst this Quire.
My second bird did take her flight
And with her mate flew out of sight.
Southward they both their course did bend,
And Seasons twain they there did spend,
Till after blown by Southern gales
They Norward steer’d with filled sails.
A prettier bird was no where seen,
Along the Beach, among the treen.
I have a third of colour white
On whom I plac’d no small delight,
Coupled with mate loving and true,
Hath also bid her Dame adieu.
And where Aurora first appears,
She now hath percht to spend her years.
One to the Academy flew
To chat among that learned crew.
Ambition moves still in his breast
That he might chant above the rest,
Striving for more than to do well,
That nightingales he might excell.
My fifth, whose down is yet scarce gone,
Is ‘mongst the shrubs and bushes flown
And as his wings increase in strength
On higher boughs he’ll perch at length.
My other three still with me nest
Until they’re grown, then as the rest,
Or here or there, they’ll take their flight,
As is ordain’d, so shall they light.
If birds could weep, then would my tears
Let others know what are my fears
Lest this my brood some harm should catch
And be surpris’d for want of watch
Whilst pecking corn and void of care
They fall un’wares in Fowler’s snare;
Or whilst on trees they sit and sing
Some untoward boy at them do fling,
Or whilst allur’d with bell and glass
The net be spread and caught, alas;
Or lest by Lime-twigs they be foil’d;
Or by some greedy hawks be spoil’d.
O would, my young, ye saw my breast
And knew what thoughts there sadly rest.
Great was my pain when I you bred,
Great was my care when I you fed.
Long did I keep you soft and warm
And with my wings kept off all harm.
My cares are more, and fears, than ever,
My throbs such now as ‘fore were never.
Alas, my birds, you wisdom want
Of perils you are ignorant.
Oft times in grass, on trees, in flight,
Sore accidents on you may light.
O to your safety have an eye,
So happy may you live and die.
Mean while, my days in tunes I’ll spend
Till my weak lays with me shall end.
In shady woods I’ll sit and sing
And things that past, to mind I’ll bring.
Once young and pleasant, as are you,
But former toys (no joys) adieu!
My age I will not once lament
But sing, my time so near is spent,
And from the top bough take my flight
Into a country beyond sight
Where old ones instantly grow young
And there with seraphims set song.
No seasons cold, nor storms they see
But spring lasts to eternity.
When each of you shall in your nest
Among your young ones take your rest,
In chirping languages oft them tell
You had a Dame that lov’d you well,
That did what could be done for young
And nurst you up till you were strong
And ‘fore she once would let you fly
She shew’d you joy and misery,
Taught what was good, and what was ill,
What would save life, and what would kill.
Thus gone, amongst you I may live,
And dead, yet speak and counsel give.
Farewell, my birds, farewell, adieu,
I happy am, if well with you.
Source: The Complete Works of Anne Bradstreet (1981)
Subjects: Living, Parenthood, Time &amp; Brevity, Relationships, Family &amp; Ancestors, Nature, Animals, Weather, Social Commentaries, Gender &amp; Sexuality
Poet's Region: U.S., New England
Poetic Terms: Couplet ]]></description><link>2.5_1650-bradstreet,-anne-poemas.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/2.5_1650 - Bradstreet, Anne - Poemas.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 02:50:23 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Anne Bradstreet]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/anne-bradstreet.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/anne-bradstreet.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/Images/Anne Bradstreet.png</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 02:49:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>colonia-de-la-bahía-de-massachusetts.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/Colonia de la Bahía de Massachusetts.md</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[MassColony]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/masscolony.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/masscolony.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/Images/MassColony.jpg</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/masscolony.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="images/masscolony.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Facts-About-Massachusetts-Colony]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/facts-about-massachusetts-colony.jpg" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/facts-about-massachusetts-colony.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/Images/Facts-About-Massachusetts-Colony.jpg</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:01 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="images/facts-about-massachusetts-colony.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="images/facts-about-massachusetts-colony.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Masscolony 1630-1691]]></title><description><![CDATA[<img src="images/masscolony-1630-1691.png" target="_self">]]></description><link>images/masscolony-1630-1691.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/Images/Masscolony 1630-1691.png</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 23:59:28 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="." length="0" type="false"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="."&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[01_Timeline_Textos]]></title><description><![CDATA[Estos textos definen las herramientas conceptuales para analizar el resto de la historia.
Davey, A. K. - "The Meaning of Culture" 2 Spencer-Oatey, H. - "What is culture?" (2012) 3 Hofstede, G. - "Dimensions of national Cultures" 4 Riccardi Pellegrino - "On the 'Encounter' of Cultures" 5 Contexto: Llegada del Mayflower (1620), colonias de Nueva Inglaterra, conflicto con Nativos.Fuentes Primarias (Documentos de la época)
1623: <a data-href="02.1_1623 - Frethorne, Richard - Letter to His Parents" href="02.1_1623-frethorne,-richard-letter-to-his-parents.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">02.1_1623 - Frethorne, Richard - Letter to His Parents</a> (La dura realidad de Jamestown) 6 done! <br>1630: <a data-href="02.3_1630 - Winthrop, John - A Model of Christian Charity" href="02.3_1630-winthrop,-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">02.3_1630 - Winthrop, John - A Model of Christian Charity</a> (Sermón puritano, "City upon a Hill") 7 done! <br>c. 1650: <a data-href="2.5_1650 - Bradstreet, Anne - Poemas" href="2.5_1650-bradstreet,-anne-poemas.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">2.5_1650 - Bradstreet, Anne - Poemas</a> 8 1682: Rowlandson, Mary - "A Narrative of the Captivity..." (Narrativa de cautiverio) 9 Fuentes Secundarias (Análisis histórico)
"The Reformation" (History Channel) 10 "Pilgrims and Puritans" (Virgin.edu) 11 "The collision of English and Native American Cultures" (Henretta &amp; Nobles) 12 Contexto: Ilustración, Independencia de EE.UU. (1776), consolidación de la esclavitud.Fuentes Primarias
1727: Colden, Cadwallader - "The History of the Five Indian Nations" 13 1754-1772: Woolman, John - "Journal" (Perspectiva cuáquera/abolicionista temprana) 14 1773: Wheatley, Phillis - "On Being Brought from Africa to America" 15 1776: Paine, Thomas - "Common Sense" y "The Crisis" 16161616 1776: Jefferson et al. - "The Declaration of Independence" 17 1776: Adams, Abigail &amp; John - Cartas ("Remember the Ladies") 18 1782: De Crèvecoeur, J. Hector - "Letters from an American Farmer" (¿Qué es un americano?) 19 1784: Franklin, Benjamin - "Remarks on the Politeness of the Savages..." 20 1780s: Freneau, Philip - "The Indian Student" &amp; "The Indian Burying Ground" 21 1790: Sargent Murray, Judith - "On the Equality of the Sexes" 22 1792: Burns, Robert - "The slave's lament" 23 Fuentes Secundarias
"The Agricultural Revolution" (Lumen Learning / Britain Express) 24242424 Bonwick, C. - "The Coming of Revolution" (1991) 25 Contexto: Era Victoriana, Expansión al Oeste, Guerra Civil (1861-65), fin de la esclavitud.Fuentes Primarias
1845: Douglass, Frederick - Narrative of the Life... 26 1848: Stanton, Elizabeth - "Seneca Falls Declaration" (Derechos de la mujer) 27 1851: Truth, Sojourner - "Ain't I a woman?" 28 1852: Douglass, Frederick - "What to the Slave is the Fourth July?" 29 1852: Rudd, Lydia - "Notes by the Wayside..." (Diario de viaje al Oeste) 30 1854: Chief Seattle - "Treaty Oration" 31 1861/1865: Lincoln, Abraham - Inaugural Addresses 32 1865: "The Black Code of St. Landry's Parish" (Leyes segregacionistas post-guerra) 33 1872: Harper, Frances Ellen - "The slave auction" 34 1872: Justice Bradley - "Women's Separate Spheres" (Fallo judicial) 35 1887: Dawes Act (Legislación sobre tierras indígenas) 36 1892: Chopin, Kate - "Desiree's baby" (Cuento sobre raza y origen) 37 1893: Turner, Frederick J. - "The Significance of the Frontier..." (Tesis de la frontera) 38 1895: Washington, Booker T. - "Atlanta Exposition Address" 39 Fuentes Secundarias
Taylor, Barilla - "The role of women in the Industrial Revolution" 40 Wojtczak, Helena - "Women Status in Mid 19th-Century England" 41 Contexto: Guerras Mundiales, Movimiento por los Derechos Civiles, Feminismo de 2da ola.Fuentes Primarias (Literarias y Discursivas)
1926: Hughes, Langston - "I, too" (Harlem Renaissance) 42 1942: Walker, Margaret - "For my people" 43 1963: Friedan, Betty - "The Problem that Has No Name" (Mística de la feminidad) 44 1963: King, Martin Luther - "I Have a Dream" 45 1969: Angelou, Maya - "Caged Bird" 46 1978: Angelou, Maya - "Still I rise" 47 1983: Nichols, Grace - I is a Long Memoried Woman 48 1994: Hobsbawm, Eric - "The Century: A Bird's Eye View" (Análisis histórico) 49 Fuentes Secundarias
Banner, L. - "The American Woman from 1900 to the First World War" 50 Chafe, W. - "The revival of feminism" (1972) 51 Hoxie, F. - "Indian-Whites Relations... 1900 to the Present" (1996) 52 Contexto: Globalización, Presidencia de Obama, BLM, Migraciones.Fuentes Primarias y Ensayos Actuales
2005: Datesman et al. - American Ways (Libro de texto cultural) 53 2009: Obama, Barack - Inaugural Address 54 2009: Hsu, Hua - "The End of White America?" 55 2015: Betts, Alexander - "Human migration will be a defining issue..." 56 2020: ADL - "George Floyd, racism and law enforcement" 57 2021: Greenidge, K. - "Black spirituals as poetry and resistance" 58 ]]></description><link>01_timeline_textos.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/01_Timeline_Textos.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 23:26:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[02.3_1630 - Winthrop, John - A Model of Christian Charity]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-href="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity" href="02.4_vocabulario-y-conceptos-históricos-winthrop-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity</a>John Winthrop, "A Modell of Christian Charity"New England's Puritans dissented not only from the Church of England, but from England's social and political order as well. Seeking alternatives to established institutions, they turned on the one hand to Scripture and on the other to their common experience for precedents. Of this extraordinarily learned and articulate group (the Massachusetts Bay Colony in the seventeenth century boasted more college graduates per capita than England itself), few gave more careful thought to the purposes of the Puritans' "errand into the wilderness" or to the proper foundations for the colony's institutions than, John Winthrop (1588-1649).Winthrop was a representative of the new gentry that flourished under the Tudor regime. His grandfather, Adam Winthrop, was a country boy who went to London, made a fortune as a clothier, and then purchased a manor (one of the many properties seized by Henry VIII from the church). His son, also named Adam, trained as a lawyer, but spent his life farming and governing his estate in Suffolk. The habit of governing others came naturally to John Winthrop. After attending Trinity College, Cambridge for two years, he returned home, where he was appointed Justice of the Peace and, a few years later, steward -- in which capacity he acted as his father's chief financial and administrative officer.Despite his privileged position, John Winthrop, like many other educated Englishmen of the period, became increasingly disenchanted with corrupt and oppressive Stuart monarchy. When Charles I decided in the spring of 1629 to rule without parliamentary consent, imprisoned Puritan parliamentary leaders, and banned Puritans from the practice of law, Winthrop decided to emigrate.While en route to New England in 1630, on board the Arabella, Winthrop wrote an essay on charity (which he presumably preached as a sermon) which sought to apply scriptural virtues to the peculiar circumstances and challenges the colonists would face in creating their new social and political order. A number of themes which become central to American philanthropic traditions are first articulated here: 1) efforts to reconcile the problem of spiritual and political equality with economic inequality; 2) concerns about the relations between the good of individuals and the good of the community; 3) the conception of community as a voluntary -- contractual -- bond between individuals; 4) a focus on the particular obligations of the rich towards the poor; 4) the conception of mission as the basis for formulating specific institutional goals and objectives.It is important to note that Winthrop does not mention private institutions: he, like many Puritans, rejected the idea of endowed institutions because of their association with Stuart corruption. For him, charity retains an interpersonal rather than an institutional emphasis. Further, he assumes that the work of society will be done by public institutions of church and State. Notably, Winthrop did not suggest that charity should extend beyond the convenanted group of believers. The notion of universal benevolence would have to wait until a more enlightened age.A Modell of Christian CharityWrittenOn board the Arabella,On the Atlantic Ocean.By the Honorable JOHN WINTHROP Esquire.In his passage, (with a great Company of Religious People,of which Christian Tribes he was the Brave Leader and famousGovernor;) from the Island of Great Brittaine, to New Englandin North America. Anno 1630.God Almightie in his most holy and wise providence hath so disposed of the Condicion of mankind, as in all times some must be rich some poore, some high and eminent in power and dignitie; others meane and in subjection.THE REASON HEREOF.
<br>Reas: First, to hold conformity with the rest of his works, being delighted to shewe forthe the glory of his wisdome in the variety and difference of the Creatures and the glory of his power, in ordering all these differences for the preservacion and good of the whole, and the glory of his greatnes that as it is the glory of princes to have many officers, soe this great King will have many <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity > ^7upjrs" data-href="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity#^7upjrs" href="02.4_vocabulario-y-conceptos-históricos-winthrop-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html#^7upjrs" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stewards</a> counting himselfe more honored in dispenceing his guifts to man by man, than if he did it by his owne immediate hand.
Reas: Secondly, That he might have the more occasion to manifest the work of his Spirit: first, upon the wicked in moderateing and restraineing them; so that the
riche and mighty should not eate upp the poore, mor the poore, and dispised rise up against their superiours, and shake off theire yoake; 2ly in the regenerate in exerciseing his graces in them, as in the greate ones, their love mercy, gentlenes, temperance etc., in the poore and inferior sorte, theire faithe patience, obedience, etc.ExplicaciónEsta sección es fundamental porque Winthrop está respondiendo a la pregunta teológica: "¿Por qué Dios permite (o diseña) que haya desigualdad social, con unos muy ricos y otros muy pobres?"
Aquí te explico punto por punto lo que Winthrop argumenta en esos dos párrafos: Winthrop argumenta que la desigualdad es una decisión estética y administrativa de Dios. La Gloria de la Variedad: Dios se deleita en la diversidad de sus criaturas (animales, plantas, estrellas). De la misma manera, quiere ver variedad en la humanidad (diferentes niveles de riqueza y poder) para mostrar la gloria de su sabiduría. La Preservación del Todo: Winthrop cree que estas diferencias están ordenadas para "la preservación y el bien del todo". Es decir, la sociedad funciona como una máquina donde cada pieza tiene un tamaño diferente para que el mecanismo funcione. La Metáfora del Rey y los Mayordomos (Stewards): Esta es la parte clave. Winthrop dice que un Príncipe glorioso no hace todo el trabajo él mismo; tiene muchos "oficiales". De igual modo, Dios (el Gran Rey) usa a los ricos como "Stewards" (Administradores/Mayordomos). El concepto: Dios podría dar dinero directamente a los pobres por un milagro ("his owne immediate hand"), pero prefiere darle el dinero a los ricos para que ellos lo distribuyan ("dispenceing his guifts to man by man"). Esto honra más a Dios porque crea una cadena de servicio. Aquí Winthrop explica la función moral de la desigualdad. Dios usa la diferencia de clases para controlar a los malvados y perfeccionar a los buenos ("los regenerados"). Winthrop tiene una visión pesimista de la naturaleza humana. Sin el control divino y la estructura social: Los Ricos: Se comerían vivos a los pobres ("eate upp the poore"). Es una metáfora de explotación extrema. Los Pobres: Se rebelarían violentamente contra sus superiores ("rise up against their superiours") y sacudirían su yugo ("shake off theire yoake"). Conclusión: La estructura social, mantenida por el Espíritu de Dios, evita que la sociedad se convierta en una guerra civil constante. Para los "regenerados" (los buenos cristianos), la desigualdad es necesaria porque sin ella no podrían practicar ciertas virtudes específicas: En resumen:
Si todos fueran ricos, nadie necesitaría misericordia. Si todos fueran pobres, nadie podría ejercer la caridad. Winthrop dice que Dios creó la desigualdad para obligar a los humanos a necesitarse unos a otros y así crear lazos sagrados (el "tejido" o knit del que hablará más adelante).
Reas: Thirdly, That every man might have need of other, and from thence they might all be knitt more nearly together in the Bond of brotherly affeccion. . . .
The deffinition which the Scripture gives us of love is this Love is the bond of perfection. First, it is a bond, or ligament. 2ly, it makes the worke perfect. There is no body but consistes of partes and that which knitts these partes together gives the body its perfeccion, because it makes eache parte soe continguous to other as thereby doe mutually participate with eache other, both in strengthe and infirmity in pleasure and paine, to instance in the most perfect of all bodies, Christ and his church make one body: the severall partes of this body considered aparte before they were united were as disproportionate and as much disordering as so many contrary quallities or elements but when christ comes and by his spirit and love knitts all these partes to himselfe and each to other, it is become the most perfect and best proportioned body in the world. . . .Explicación
Winthrop presenta la tercera razón ("3. Reas: Thirdly") de por qué existen ricos y pobres: El Propósito de la Escasez: La razón de la desigualdad es "que cada hombre pueda tener necesidad del otro" (That every man might have need of other). El Resultado: Al necesitarse mutuamente (el pobre necesita ayuda, el rico necesita a alguien a quien servir), se crea un vínculo inevitable. De esta necesidad nace el "Vínculo de afecto fraternal" (Bond of brotherly affeccion). Interpretación: Si todos fueran ricos y poderosos, vivirían aislados en su independencia. La desigualdad fuerza la comunidad. Winthrop ofrece una definición casi médica o anatómica del amor, basada en las Escrituras (The deffinition which the Scripture gives us of love): El Amor es un Tejido Conectivo: Lo define explícitamente como un "ligamento" (bond, or ligament). Función del Ligamento: Un cuerpo se compone de partes. Sin ligamentos, esas partes serían solo un montón de huesos y carne sueltos. El amor es lo que "teje" (knitts) estas partes juntas y le da al cuerpo su perfección. Contigüidad y Empatía: El ligamento hace que las partes estén tan unidas (contiguous) que "participan mutuamente" (mutually participate) en lo que le pasa a la otra. Si una parte siente dolor (paine) o placer (pleasure), o tiene fuerza (strengthe) o enfermedad (infirmity), el resto del cuerpo lo siente. Esto es una llamada a la empatía radical. Winthrop usa el ejemplo teológico máximo para ilustrar su punto social: "el cuerpo más perfecto de todos, Cristo y su iglesia hacen un solo cuerpo" (the most perfect of all bodies, Christ and his church make one body). Antes de la Unión (Caos): Consideradas por separado, las partes (las personas) son "desproporcionadas" y "desordenadas" (disproportionate and as much disordering), como elementos contrarios chocando entre sí. Un individuo sin comunidad es un caos. Después de la Unión (Perfección): Cuando Cristo viene y, mediante su Espíritu y amor, "teje" (knitts) todas estas partes consigo mismo y entre ellas, se convierte en el cuerpo "mejor proporcionado del mundo".
Here in are 4 things to be propounded: first the persons, 2ly, the worke, 3ly, the end, 4ly, the meanes.
For the persons, wee are a Company professiong our selves fellow members of Christ. In which respect onely though wee were absent from eache other many miles, and had our imploymentes as farre distant, yet wee ought to account ourselves knitt toether by this bond of love, and live in the Aquí tienes la transcripción de las páginas restantes (3, 4, 5 y 6). He mantenido la ortografía y puntuación del inglés antiguo (por ejemplo: "prividence", "Condicion", "2ly", "Citty") tal como aparece en el documento original.
Explicación
Finalmente, Winthrop baja de la teología a la realidad de su viaje: Quiénes son: Se definen como una Compañía que profesa ser "miembros compañeros de Cristo" (fellow members of Christ). La Regla de la Distancia: Argumenta que, gracias a este "ligamento", la distancia física no importa. Aunque estén ausentes el uno del otro por muchas millas (absent from eache other many miles), deben considerarse "tejidos juntos" (knitt toether) por este vínculo de amor. En resumen: Winthrop está diciendo que la sociedad que están fundando no es una empresa comercial ni una simple ciudad; es un organismo vivo. Si cortas el "ligamento" (el amor/caridad) ignorando las necesidades del vecino, el cuerpo se desmorona y muere.excercise of it, if wee would have the comforte of our being in Christ. . . .2ly. for the worke wee have in hand, it is by mutuall consent through a speciall overruleing providence, and amore then an ordinary approbation of the Churches of Christ to seeke out a place ofCohabitation and Consorteshipp under a due forme of Government both civall and ecclesiasticall. In such cases as this the care of the publique must oversway all private respects, by which not onely conscience, but meare Civil policy doth bind1e us; for it is a true rule that perticuler estates cannott subsist in the ruine of the publique.SummaryEsta sección es el "plan de acción" práctico y espiritual de Winthrop. Aquí define qué van a hacer, por qué lo hacen y cómo deben comportarse para sobrevivir. "seeke out a place of Cohabitation and Consorteshipp under a due forme of Government both civall and ecclesiasticall." Winthrop define la colonia no como un campamento comercial, sino como una sociedad estructurada: Cohabitation and Consorteshipp (Convivencia y Consorcio): No son individuos aislados buscando fortuna, sino socios que han acordado vivir juntos ("Consorteshipp"). Government both civall and ecclesiasticall (Gobierno tanto civil como eclesiástico): Winthrop establece desde el principio que necesitarán dos tipos de autoridad: Leyes civiles (magistrados, cortes) para el orden público.
Leyes eclesiásticas (iglesia) para el orden espiritual. La Regla de Oro Política: Justo después, establece la prioridad absoluta: "the care of the publique must oversway all private respects". El bien público está por encima del interés privado, porque si la colonia ("lo público") se arruina, nadie podrá salvar su propiedad privada ("particular estates").
3ly. The end is to improve our lives to doe more service to the Lord the comforte and encrease of the body of christe whereof wee are members that our selves and posterity may be the better preserved from the Common corrupcions of this evill world to serve the Lord and worke out our Salvacion under the power and purity of his holy Ordinances.Summary "preserved from the Common corrupcions of this evill world" El objetivo ("The end") no es la riqueza, sino la pureza espiritual. Quieren mejorar sus vidas para servir más a Dios y protegerse a sí mismos y a sus hijos ("posterity") de la corrupción moral que veían en Europa e Inglaterra. Buscan vivir bajo "Ordenanzas santas".4ly. for the meanes whereby this must be effected, they are 2fold, a Conformity with the worke and end we aim at, these wee see are extraordinary, therefore wee must not content our selves with usuall ordinary meanes whatsoever wee did or ought to have done when wee lived in England, the same must we doe and more allsoe where we goe. . . .Summary
Winthrop advierte que, como el objetivo es extraordinario, los medios también deben serlo ("extraordinary"). No basta con ser "buenos cristianos" como lo eran en Inglaterra; deben hacer más. "we must entertaine each other in brotherly Affeccion" Afecto Fraternal: Deben tratarse como familia. Sacrificio Económico: Deben estar dispuestos a recortar sus propios excesos ("abridge our selves of our superfluities") para suplir las necesidades de los demás. "make others Condicions our owne rejoyce together" Empatía Total: La frase completa es "make others Condicions our owne, rejoyce together" (hacer nuestras las condiciones de los otros, regocijarnos juntos). Significa que si tu vecino sufre, tú debes sentir ese sufrimiento como propio; si él celebra, tú celebras. No hay indiferencia permitida.
<br>. . . wee must be knitt together in this worke as one man, we must entertaine each other in brotherly Affeccion, we must be willing to abridge our selves of our superfluities, for the suppy of others necessities, we must uphold a familiar Commerce together in meekenes, gentlenes, patience and liberallity, wee must delight in eache other, make others Condicions our owne rejoyce together, allwayes haveing before our eyes== our Commission and Community== in the worke. . . . for wee must Consider that wee shall be as a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity > ^3s4e3d" data-href="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity#^3s4e3d" href="02.4_vocabulario-y-conceptos-históricos-winthrop-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html#^3s4e3d" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Citty upon a Hill</a> , the eies of all people are uppon us; soe that if wee shall deale falsely with our god in this worke wee have undertaken and soe cause him to withdrawe his present help from us, wee shall be made a story and a by-word through the world, we shall open the mouthes of enemies to speake evill of the wayes of god and all professours for Gods sake; wee shall shame the faces of many of gods worthy servants, and cause theire pra31yers to be turned into Curses upon us till we be consumed out of the good land whether we are going. . . .Summary "always haveing before our eyes our Commission and Community in the worke" Commission (La Comisión): Winthrop ve esto como un contrato legal con Dios. Dios les ha dado el permiso y los recursos para ir; ellos a cambio prometen construir una sociedad santa. El Riesgo: Si rompen el contrato ("deale falsely with our god"), Dios retirará su ayuda y perecerán. "wee shall be as a Citty upon a Hill, the eies of all people are uppon us" Esta es la conclusión famosa y terrible: Visibilidad Total: Ser una "Ciudad sobre una Colina" no es un premio, es una responsabilidad de alto riesgo. Significa que no pueden esconderse. El Juicio Mundial: "Los ojos de todos los pueblos están sobre nosotros". Si tienen éxito: Glorifican a Dios. Si fracasan: Se convertirán en una "historia y un refrán" (story and a by-word) de burla por todo el mundo. Avergonzarán a Dios y sus oraciones se convertirán en maldiciones hasta que sean "consumidos" (destruidos) de la tierra. Resumen: Winthrop les está diciendo: "Hemos firmado un contrato estricto con Dios. Si nos cuidamos unos a otros (amor fraternal) y ponemos a la comunidad primero, sobreviviremos y seremos un ejemplo. Si somos egoístas, todo el mundo nos verá fracasar y moriremos".Source: Edmund S. Morgan, ed., The Founding of Massachusetts: Historians and the Sources (Indianapolis, 1964).Additional Readings: David Grayson Allen, In English Ways: The Movement of Societies and the Transferal of English Local Law and Custom (Chapel Hill, 1981).David T. Konig, Law and Society in Puritan Massachusetts (1979)Perry Miller, Errand Into the Wilderness (Boston, 1956).__, The New England Mind: From Colony to Province (Boston, 1953).__, Orthodoxy in Massachusetts, 1630-1650 (New York, 1970).Edmund S. Morgan, Puritan Dilemma: The Story of John Winthrop (New York, 1958).Samuel Eliot Morison, Builders of the Bay Colony (Boston, 1930).Darrett Rutman, Winthrop's Boston (Chapel Hill, 1965). Winthrop Papers, multivolume (Boston, 1929 -).]]></description><link>02.3_1630-winthrop,-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/02.3_1630 - Winthrop, John - A Model of Christian Charity.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 22:05:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[02.1_1623 - Frethorne, Richard - Letter to His Parents]]></title><description><![CDATA[
[...] colonization in the early seventeenth century. Combatting homesickness, disease, hunger, discomfort, and isolation, Frethorne and his fellow settlers struggled to make a success of their fledgling community. As might be expected, many longed to be "redeemed out of Egypt" and return to their former lives across the Atlantic. Frethorne's correspondence reveals the poignancy of the struggle for survival waged by the class of indentured servants in the new world.
— Lisbeth Cohen, Montana State University
Loving and kind father and mother:My most humble duty remembered to you, hoping in God of your good health, as I myself am at the making hereof. This is to let you understand that I your child am in a most heavy case by reason of the nature of the country, [which] is such that it causeth much sickness, as the scurvy and the bloody flux and diverse other diseases, which maketh the body very poor and weak. And when we are sick there is nothing to comfort us; for since I came out of the ship I never ate anything but peas, and loblollie (that is, water gruel). As for deer or venison I never saw any since I came into this land. There is indeed some fowl, but we are not allowed to go and get it, but must work hard both early and late for a mess of water gruel and a mouthful of bread and beef. A mouthful of bread for a penny loaf must serve for four men which is most pitiful....People cry out day and night—Oh! that they were in England without their limbs—and would not care to lose any limb to be England again, yea, though they beg from door to door. For we live in fear of the enemy every hour, yet we have had a combat with them on the Sunday before Shrovetide,^1 and we took two alive and made slaves of them. But it was by policy, for we are in great danger; for our plantation is very weak by reason of the death and sickness of our company. For we came but twenty for the merchants, and they are half dead just; and we look every hour when two more should go. Yet there came some four other men yet to live with us, of which there is but one alive; and our Lieutenant is dead, and his father and his brother. And there was some five or six of the last year’s twenty, of which there is but three left, so that we are fain to get other men to plant with us; and yet we are but 32 to fight against 3000 if they should come. And the nighest help that we have is ten miles of us, and when the rogues overcame this place last they slew 80 persons. How then shall we do, for we lie even in their teeth? They may easily take us, but that God is merciful and can save with few as well as with many, as he showed to Gilead.^2 ...And I have nothing to comfort me, nor there is nothing to be gotten here but sickness and death, except that one had money to lay out in some things for profit. But I have nothing at all—no, not a shirt to my back but two rags (2), nor no clothes but one poor suit, nor but one pair of shoes, but one pair of stockings, but one cap, but two bands. My cloak is stolen by one of my own fellows, and to his dying hour [he] would not tell me what he did with it; but some of my fellows saw him have butter and beef out of a ship, which my cloak, I doubt [not], paid for. So that I have not a penny, nor a penny worth, to help me to either spice or sugar or strong waters, without the which one cannot live here. For as strong beer in1 England doth fatten and strengthen them, so water here doth wash and weaken these here [and] only keeps life and soul together. 2But I am not half a quarter so strong as I was in England, and all is for want of victuals; for I do protest unto you that I have eaten more in [one] day at home than I have allowed me here for a week. You have given more than my day’s allowance to a beggar at the door: and if Mr. Jackson had not relieved me, I should be in a poor case. But he like a father and she like a loving mother doth still help me.3...Goodman Jackson pitied me and made me a cabin to lie in... which comforted me more than peas or water gruel. Oh, they be very godly folks, and love me very well, and will do anything for me. And he much marvelled that you would send me a servant to the Company; he saith I had been better knocked on the head. And indeed so I find it now, to my great grief and misery; and saith that if you love me you will redeem me suddenly, for which I do entreat and beg. And if you cannot get the merchants to redeem me for some little money, then for God’s sake get a gathering or entreat some good folks to lay out some little sum of money in meal and cheese and butter and beef. Any eating meat will yield great profit. Oil and vinegar is very good; but, father, there is great loss in leaking. But for God’s sake send beef and cheese and butter, or the more of one sort and none of another. But if you send cheese, it must be very old cheese; and at the cheesemonger’s you may buy very good cheese for two pence farthing or halfpenny, that will be liked very well. But if you send cheese, you must have a care how you pack it in barrels; and you must put cooper’s chips between every cheese, or else the heat of the hold will rot them. And look whatsoever you send me—be it never so much—look, what[ever] I make of it, I will deal truly with you. I will send it over and beg the profit to redeem me; and if I die before it come, I have entreated Goodman Jackson to send you the worth of it, who hath promised he will....ExplicaciónEsta es una de las partes más conmovedoras y reveladoras de la carta. Aquí, Richard Frethorne deja de lado las descripciones generales de la colonia para hablar de su estrategia personal de supervivencia y lanzar una súplica desesperada (y manipuladora) a sus padres.
Aquí te explico los puntos clave de este fragmento desglosados por temas: Frethorne introduce a un tal Sr. Jackson (Goodman era un título para hombres respetables pero no nobles). El contraste: Mientras sus propios padres lo enviaron a sufrir, este extraño lo "compadeció" (pitied me), le construyó una cabaña y lo trató como a un hijo. La crítica indirecta: Frethorne usa a Jackson para criticar a sus padres sin hacerlo directamente. Dice que Jackson "se maravilló" de que sus padres lo hubieran enviado como sirviente y dijo que "habría sido mejor que me golpearan en la cabeza" (better knocked on the head). Es una forma brutal de decir: "Enviarme aquí fue una sentencia de muerte, y hasta un extraño se da cuenta". La palabra clave aquí es "Redeem" (Redimir/Rescatar). Frethorne quiere romper su contrato de servidumbre (indenture). Plan A: Pide a sus padres que paguen directamente a los comerciantes para cancelar su contrato. Plan B (Comercio): Si no tienen dinero ("if you cannot get the merchants to redeem me"), les propone un negocio. Les pide que hagan una colecta (get a gathering) entre vecinos para comprar comida (carne, queso, mantequilla) y enviársela a Virginia. Frethorne no solo pide comida para alimentarse, la pide para venderla. Dice: "Any eating meat will yield great profit" (Cualquier carne comestible dará gran beneficio). En la Virginia de 1623, la comida escaseaba tanto que valía mucho más que el dinero. Su plan es recibir esa comida, venderla en la colonia y usar las ganancias (profit) para comprar su propia libertad. Es fascinante ver cómo Frethorne da instrucciones muy técnicas sobre cómo enviar la mercancía, lo que demuestra lo difícil que era el transporte transatlántico: El queso: Debe ser "very old cheese" (queso muy curado) para que aguante el viaje. El embalaje: Les instruye poner "cooper’s chips" (virutas de madera de tonelero) entre cada queso. La razón: Si no lo hacen, el calor de la bodega del barco (the heat of the hold) hará que se pudran (rot). El párrafo termina con una nota muy oscura que refleja la realidad de la mortalidad en la colonia: Frethorne promete ser honesto con las ganancias (deal truly with you). Pero añade: "y si muero antes de que llegue [la comida]". Ha dejado instrucciones a Goodman Jackson para que, si Richard muere antes de que llegue el envío, Jackson venda la comida y devuelva el dinero a los padres en Inglaterra. Esto demuestra que Frethorne sabe que la muerte es inminente. En resumen: Este párrafo es un grito de auxilio disfrazado de plan de negocios. Frethorne les está diciendo a sus padres: "Me equivoqué al venir, un extraño me cuida mejor que ustedes, envíenme mercancía para comprar mi libertad o moriré aquí pronto".Good father, do not forget me, but have mercy and pity my miserable case. I know if you did but see me, you would weep to see me; for I have but one suit.... Wherefore, for God’s sake, pity me. I pray you to remember my love to all my friends and kindred. I hope all my brothers and sisters are in good health, and as for my part I have set down my resolution that certainly will be; that is, that the answer of this letter will be life or death to me. Therefore good father, send as soon as you can; and if you send me any thing let this be the mark.ROTRichard Frethorne,Martin's HundredAll these died out of my master’s house, since I came; and we came in but at Christmas, and this is the 20th day of March. And the sailors say that there is two-thirds of the 150 dead already. And thus I end, praying to God to send me good success that I may be redeemed out of Egypt. So vale in Christo.Loving father, I pray you to use this man very exceeding kindly, for he hath done much for me, both on my journey and since. I entreat you not to forget me, but by any means redeem me; for this day we hear that there is 26 of Englishmen slain by the Indians. And they have taken a pinnace of Mr. Pountis, and have gotten pieces, armor, swords, all things fit for war; so that they may now steal upon us and we cannot know them from English till it is too late—that they be upon us—and then there is no mercy. Therefore if you love or respect me as your child, release me from the bondage and save my life. Now you may save me, or let me be slain with infidels. Ask this man—he knoweth that all is true and just that I say here. If you do redeem me, the Company must send for me to my Mr. Harrod; for so is this Master’s name. April, the second day.Your loving son,Richard FrethorneMoreover, on the third day of April we heard that after these rogues had gotten the pinnace and had taken all furnitures [such] as pieces, swords, armor, coats of mail, powder, shot and all the things that they had to trade withal, they killed the Captain and cut off his head. And rowing with the tail of the boat foremost, they set up a pole and put the Captain’s head upon it, and so rowed home. Then the Devil set them on again, so that they furnished about 200 canoes with above 1000 Indians, and came, and thought to have taken the ship; but she was too quick for them—which thing was very much talked of, for they always feared a ship. But now the rogues grow very bold and can use pieces, some of them, as well or better than an Englishman; for an Indian did shoot with Mr. Charles, my master’s kinsman, at a mark of white paper, and he hit it at the first, but Mr. Charles could not hit it. But see the envy of these slaves, for when they could not take the ship, then our men saw them threaten Accomack, that is the next plantation. And now there is no way but starving: . . . For they had no crop last year by reason of these rogues, so that we have no corn but as ships do relieve us, nor we shall hardly have any crop this year; and we are as like to perish first as any plantation. For we have but two hogsheads of meal left to serve us this two months, . . . that is but a halfpennyloaf a day for a man. Is it not strange to me, think you? But what will it be when we shall go a month or two and never see a bit of bread, as my master doth say we must do? And he said he is not able to keep us all. Then we shall be turned up to the land and eat barks of trees or molds of the ground; therefore with weeping tears I beg of you to help me. Oh, that you did see my daily and hourly sighs, groans, and tears, and thumps that I afford mine own breast, and rue and curse the time of my birth, with holy Job. I thought no head had been able to hold so much water as hath and doth daily flow from mine eyes.But this is certain: I never felt the want of father and mother till now; but now, dear friends, full well I know and rue it, although it were too late before I knew it....Your loving son,Richard FrethorneVirginia, 3rd April, ExplicaciónEste fragmento es la conclusión de la carta y constituye la parte más dramática y desesperada. Aquí Frethorne narra el colapso total de la seguridad en la colonia debido a la guerra con los nativos y la hambruna inminente.
Aquí te explico los puntos clave que están ocurriendo en este texto: Frethorne comienza actualizando el recuento de bajas. El dato: Llegaron en Navidad con 150 personas. Para el 20 de marzo, los marineros estiman que dos tercios ya han muerto. "Redeemed out of Egypt": Frethorne usa una metáfora bíblica. Compara su situación en Virginia con la esclavitud de los israelitas en el Egipto faraónico. Pedir ser "redimido de Egipto" significa ser rescatado de la esclavitud y la muerte. El 2 de abril y el 3 de abril, la situación empeora drásticamente. El robo estratégico: Los nativos (a los que llama "rogues" o bribones) capturaron una pinaza (un barco pequeño de exploración) perteneciente al Sr. Pountis. Con el barco, consiguieron un arsenal: armaduras, espadas, pólvora y armas de fuego. Guerra psicológica: Frethorne relata una escena de terror. Los nativos mataron al Capitán, le cortaron la cabeza y la pusieron en un poste en el barco capturado, remando con la popa hacia adelante para exhibir el trofeo mientras regresaban a su territorio. El ataque masivo: Envalentonados, reunieron 200 canoas y 1000 guerreros para intentar capturar el barco principal, aunque no lo lograron. Esta es quizás la parte que más miedo le da a Frethorne. Adaptación indígena: Los colonos dependían de sus armas de fuego ("pieces") para mantener la ventaja. Sin embargo, Frethorne admite que ahora los nativos "se han vuelto muy audaces y pueden usar las armas... tan bien o mejor que un inglés". La prueba: Cuenta una anécdota humillante donde un nativo compitió disparando a un blanco de papel contra el Sr. Charles (pariente del amo de Frethorne). El nativo acertó al primer intento, mientras que el inglés falló. Esto significaba que los colonos ya no estaban seguros ni siquiera con sus mosquetes. Debido a la guerra, no pudieron plantar cultivos el año anterior y no pueden plantar este año porque los nativos los acechan. Raciones: Solo quedan dos barriles (hogsheads) de harina para dos meses. Eso equivale a medio panecillo ("halfpenny loaf") al día por persona. Medidas desesperadas: Su amo ha admitido que no puede mantenerlos a todos. Frethorne anticipa que pronto los echarán al campo a comer "cortezas de árboles o moho de la tierra" (barks of trees or molds of the ground). El texto termina con Frethorne llorando, golpeándose el pecho y maldiciendo el momento de su nacimiento, comparándose con el Santo Job (figura bíblica que lo perdió todo y sufrió plagas). Termina con una confesión desgarradora: nunca valoró a sus padres hasta ahora, cuando ya es demasiado tarde.
En resumen, este fragmento explica por qué la carta es tan urgente: no se trata solo de trabajo duro, se enfrentan a un enemigo que ha aprendido a usar sus propias armas y a una hambruna que los obligará a comer tierra.**Footnotes:
Shrovetide: The three days before Ash Wednesday, former76ly set aside as a period of confession and a time of festivity preceding Lent in Christian77 practice.
Gilead: A region east of the Jordan River settled in biblical times by, among others, Is87raelites who were successfully defended in battle against vastly superior numbers of invaders by Judas Maccabeus and his warriors.
Pinnace: A small sailing boat, often used as a scout for a larger vessel.
]]></description><link>02.1_1623-frethorne,-richard-letter-to-his-parents.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/02.1_1623 - Frethorne, Richard - Letter to His Parents.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 22:02:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[index]]></title><description><![CDATA[Meta: Examen Final Febrero 2025
Programa: <a data-href="Programa_2025" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Programa_2025</a><br>
Tema Especial (Oral): <a data-href="Tema_Seleccionado" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Tema_Seleccionado</a>
Unidades:<br>
<a data-href="Unidad_1_Encuentro_de_Culturas" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_1_Encuentro_de_Culturas</a><br>
<a data-href="Unidad_2_Tiempos_Coloniales" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_2_Tiempos_Coloniales</a><br>
<a data-href="Unidad_3_Siglo_XVIII" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_3_Siglo_XVIII</a><br>
<a data-href="Unidad_4_Siglo_XIX" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_4_Siglo_XIX</a><br>
<a data-href="Unidad_5_Siglos_XX_XXI" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_5_Siglos_XX_XXI</a>]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/index.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:05:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[02.3_Winthrop, John - A Model of Christian Charity]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a data-href="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity" href="02.4_vocabulario-y-conceptos-históricos-winthrop-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity</a>John Winthrop, "A Modell of Christian Charity"New England's Puritans dissented not only from the Church of England, but from England's social and political order as well. Seeking alternatives to established institutions, they turned on the one hand to Scripture and on the other to their common experience for precedents. Of this extraordinarily learned and articulate group (the Massachusetts Bay Colony in the seventeenth century boasted more college graduates per capita than England itself), few gave more careful thought to the purposes of the Puritans' "errand into the wilderness" or to the proper foundations for the colony's institutions than, John Winthrop (1588-1649).Winthrop was a representative of the new gentry that flourished under the Tudor regime. His grandfather, Adam Winthrop, was a country boy who went to London, made a fortune as a clothier, and then purchased a manor (one of the many properties seized by Henry VIII from the church). His son, also named Adam, trained as a lawyer, but spent his life farming and governing his estate in Suffolk. The habit of governing others came naturally to John Winthrop. After attending Trinity College, Cambridge for two years, he returned home, where he was appointed Justice of the Peace and, a few years later, steward -- in which capacity he acted as his father's chief financial and administrative officer.Despite his privileged position, John Winthrop, like many other educated Englishmen of the period, became increasingly disenchanted with corrupt and oppressive Stuart monarchy. When Charles I decided in the spring of 1629 to rule without parliamentary consent, imprisoned Puritan parliamentary leaders, and banned Puritans from the practice of law, Winthrop decided to emigrate.While en route to New England in 1630, on board the Arabella, Winthrop wrote an essay on charity (which he presumably preached as a sermon) which sought to apply scriptural virtues to the peculiar circumstances and challenges the colonists would face in creating their new social and political order. A number of themes which become central to American philanthropic traditions are first articulated here: 1) efforts to reconcile the problem of spiritual and political equality with economic inequality; 2) concerns about the relations between the good of individuals and the good of the community; 3) the conception of community as a voluntary -- contractual -- bond between individuals; 4) a focus on the particular obligations of the rich towards the poor; 4) the conception of mission as the basis for formulating specific institutional goals and objectives.It is important to note that Winthrop does not mention private institutions: he, like many Puritans, rejected the idea of endowed institutions because of their association with Stuart corruption. For him, charity retains an interpersonal rather than an institutional emphasis. Further, he assumes that the work of society will be done by public institutions of church and State. Notably, Winthrop did not suggest that charity should extend beyond the convenanted group of believers. The notion of universal benevolence would have to wait until a more enlightened age.A Modell of Christian CharityWrittenOn board the Arabella,On the Atlantic Ocean.By the Honorable JOHN WINTHROP Esquire.In his passage, (with a great Company of Religious People,of which Christian Tribes he was the Brave Leader and famousGovernor;) from the Island of Great Brittaine, to New Englandin North America. Anno 1630.God Almightie in his most holy and wise providence hath so disposed of the Condicion of mankind, as in all times some must be rich some poore, some high and eminent in power and dignitie; others meane and in subjection.THE REASON HEREOF.
<br>Reas: First, to hold conformity with the rest of his works, being delighted to shewe forthe the glory of his wisdome in the variety and difference of the Creatures and the glory of his power, in ordering all these differences for the preservacion and good of the whole, and the glory of his greatnes that as it is the glory of princes to have many officers, soe this great King will have many <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity > ^7upjrs" data-href="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity#^7upjrs" href="02.4_vocabulario-y-conceptos-históricos-winthrop-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html#^7upjrs" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stewards</a> counting himselfe more honored in dispenceing his guifts to man by man, than if he did it by his owne immediate hand.
Reas: Secondly, That he might have the more occasion to manifest the work of his Spirit: first, upon the wicked in moderateing and restraineing them; so that the
riche and mighty should not eate upp the poore, mor the poore, and dispised rise up against their superiours, and shake off theire yoake; 2ly in the regenerate in exerciseing his graces in them, as in the greate ones, their love mercy, gentlenes, temperance etc., in the poore and inferior sorte, theire faithe patience, obedience, etc.ExplicaciónEsta sección es fundamental porque Winthrop está respondiendo a la pregunta teológica: "¿Por qué Dios permite (o diseña) que haya desigualdad social, con unos muy ricos y otros muy pobres?"
Aquí te explico punto por punto lo que Winthrop argumenta en esos dos párrafos: Winthrop argumenta que la desigualdad es una decisión estética y administrativa de Dios. La Gloria de la Variedad: Dios se deleita en la diversidad de sus criaturas (animales, plantas, estrellas). De la misma manera, quiere ver variedad en la humanidad (diferentes niveles de riqueza y poder) para mostrar la gloria de su sabiduría. La Preservación del Todo: Winthrop cree que estas diferencias están ordenadas para "la preservación y el bien del todo". Es decir, la sociedad funciona como una máquina donde cada pieza tiene un tamaño diferente para que el mecanismo funcione. La Metáfora del Rey y los Mayordomos (Stewards): Esta es la parte clave. Winthrop dice que un Príncipe glorioso no hace todo el trabajo él mismo; tiene muchos "oficiales". De igual modo, Dios (el Gran Rey) usa a los ricos como "Stewards" (Administradores/Mayordomos). El concepto: Dios podría dar dinero directamente a los pobres por un milagro ("his owne immediate hand"), pero prefiere darle el dinero a los ricos para que ellos lo distribuyan ("dispenceing his guifts to man by man"). Esto honra más a Dios porque crea una cadena de servicio. Aquí Winthrop explica la función moral de la desigualdad. Dios usa la diferencia de clases para controlar a los malvados y perfeccionar a los buenos ("los regenerados"). Winthrop tiene una visión pesimista de la naturaleza humana. Sin el control divino y la estructura social: Los Ricos: Se comerían vivos a los pobres ("eate upp the poore"). Es una metáfora de explotación extrema. Los Pobres: Se rebelarían violentamente contra sus superiores ("rise up against their superiours") y sacudirían su yugo ("shake off theire yoake"). Conclusión: La estructura social, mantenida por el Espíritu de Dios, evita que la sociedad se convierta en una guerra civil constante. Para los "regenerados" (los buenos cristianos), la desigualdad es necesaria porque sin ella no podrían practicar ciertas virtudes específicas: En resumen:
Si todos fueran ricos, nadie necesitaría misericordia. Si todos fueran pobres, nadie podría ejercer la caridad. Winthrop dice que Dios creó la desigualdad para obligar a los humanos a necesitarse unos a otros y así crear lazos sagrados (el "tejido" o knit del que hablará más adelante).
Reas: Thirdly, That every man might have need of other, and from thence they might all be knitt more nearly together in the Bond of brotherly affeccion. . . .
The deffinition which the Scripture gives us of love is this Love is the bond of perfection. First, it is a bond, or ligament. 2ly, it makes the worke perfect. There is no body but consistes of partes and that which knitts these partes together gives the body its perfeccion, because it makes eache parte soe continguous to other as thereby doe mutually participate with eache other, both in strengthe and infirmity in pleasure and paine, to instance in the most perfect of all bodies, Christ and his church make one body: the severall partes of this body considered aparte before they were united were as disproportionate and as much disordering as so many contrary quallities or elements but when christ comes and by his spirit and love knitts all these partes to himselfe and each to other, it is become the most perfect and best proportioned body in the world. . . .Explicación
Winthrop presenta la tercera razón ("3. Reas: Thirdly") de por qué existen ricos y pobres: El Propósito de la Escasez: La razón de la desigualdad es "que cada hombre pueda tener necesidad del otro" (That every man might have need of other). El Resultado: Al necesitarse mutuamente (el pobre necesita ayuda, el rico necesita a alguien a quien servir), se crea un vínculo inevitable. De esta necesidad nace el "Vínculo de afecto fraternal" (Bond of brotherly affeccion). Interpretación: Si todos fueran ricos y poderosos, vivirían aislados en su independencia. La desigualdad fuerza la comunidad. Winthrop ofrece una definición casi médica o anatómica del amor, basada en las Escrituras (The deffinition which the Scripture gives us of love): El Amor es un Tejido Conectivo: Lo define explícitamente como un "ligamento" (bond, or ligament). Función del Ligamento: Un cuerpo se compone de partes. Sin ligamentos, esas partes serían solo un montón de huesos y carne sueltos. El amor es lo que "teje" (knitts) estas partes juntas y le da al cuerpo su perfección. Contigüidad y Empatía: El ligamento hace que las partes estén tan unidas (contiguous) que "participan mutuamente" (mutually participate) en lo que le pasa a la otra. Si una parte siente dolor (paine) o placer (pleasure), o tiene fuerza (strengthe) o enfermedad (infirmity), el resto del cuerpo lo siente. Esto es una llamada a la empatía radical. Winthrop usa el ejemplo teológico máximo para ilustrar su punto social: "el cuerpo más perfecto de todos, Cristo y su iglesia hacen un solo cuerpo" (the most perfect of all bodies, Christ and his church make one body). Antes de la Unión (Caos): Consideradas por separado, las partes (las personas) son "desproporcionadas" y "desordenadas" (disproportionate and as much disordering), como elementos contrarios chocando entre sí. Un individuo sin comunidad es un caos. Después de la Unión (Perfección): Cuando Cristo viene y, mediante su Espíritu y amor, "teje" (knitts) todas estas partes consigo mismo y entre ellas, se convierte en el cuerpo "mejor proporcionado del mundo".
Here in are 4 things to be propounded: first the persons, 2ly, the worke, 3ly, the end, 4ly, the meanes.
For the persons, wee are a Company professiong our selves fellow members of Christ. In which respect onely though wee were absent from eache other many miles, and had our imploymentes as farre distant, yet wee ought to account ourselves knitt toether by this bond of love, and live in the Aquí tienes la transcripción de las páginas restantes (3, 4, 5 y 6). He mantenido la ortografía y puntuación del inglés antiguo (por ejemplo: "prividence", "Condicion", "2ly", "Citty") tal como aparece en el documento original.
Explicación
Finalmente, Winthrop baja de la teología a la realidad de su viaje: Quiénes son: Se definen como una Compañía que profesa ser "miembros compañeros de Cristo" (fellow members of Christ). La Regla de la Distancia: Argumenta que, gracias a este "ligamento", la distancia física no importa. Aunque estén ausentes el uno del otro por muchas millas (absent from eache other many miles), deben considerarse "tejidos juntos" (knitt toether) por este vínculo de amor. En resumen: Winthrop está diciendo que la sociedad que están fundando no es una empresa comercial ni una simple ciudad; es un organismo vivo. Si cortas el "ligamento" (el amor/caridad) ignorando las necesidades del vecino, el cuerpo se desmorona y muere.excercise of it, if wee would have the comforte of our being in Christ. . . .2ly. for the worke wee have in hand, it is by mutuall consent through a speciall overruleing providence, and amore then an ordinary approbation of the Churches of Christ to seeke out a place ofCohabitation and Consorteshipp under a due forme of Government both civall and ecclesiasticall. In such cases as this the care of the publique must oversway all private respects, by which not onely conscience, but meare Civil policy doth bind1e us; for it is a true rule that perticuler estates cannott subsist in the ruine of the publique.SummaryEsta sección es el "plan de acción" práctico y espiritual de Winthrop. Aquí define qué van a hacer, por qué lo hacen y cómo deben comportarse para sobrevivir. "seeke out a place of Cohabitation and Consorteshipp under a due forme of Government both civall and ecclesiasticall." Winthrop define la colonia no como un campamento comercial, sino como una sociedad estructurada: Cohabitation and Consorteshipp (Convivencia y Consorcio): No son individuos aislados buscando fortuna, sino socios que han acordado vivir juntos ("Consorteshipp"). Government both civall and ecclesiasticall (Gobierno tanto civil como eclesiástico): Winthrop establece desde el principio que necesitarán dos tipos de autoridad: Leyes civiles (magistrados, cortes) para el orden público.
Leyes eclesiásticas (iglesia) para el orden espiritual. La Regla de Oro Política: Justo después, establece la prioridad absoluta: "the care of the publique must oversway all private respects". El bien público está por encima del interés privado, porque si la colonia ("lo público") se arruina, nadie podrá salvar su propiedad privada ("particular estates").
3ly. The end is to improve our lives to doe more service to the Lord the comforte and encrease of the body of christe whereof wee are members that our selves and posterity may be the better preserved from the Common corrupcions of this evill world to serve the Lord and worke out our Salvacion under the power and purity of his holy Ordinances.Summary "preserved from the Common corrupcions of this evill world" El objetivo ("The end") no es la riqueza, sino la pureza espiritual. Quieren mejorar sus vidas para servir más a Dios y protegerse a sí mismos y a sus hijos ("posterity") de la corrupción moral que veían en Europa e Inglaterra. Buscan vivir bajo "Ordenanzas santas".4ly. for the meanes whereby this must be effected, they are 2fold, a Conformity with the worke and end we aim at, these wee see are extraordinary, therefore wee must not content our selves with usuall ordinary meanes whatsoever wee did or ought to have done when wee lived in England, the same must we doe and more allsoe where we goe. . . .Summary
Winthrop advierte que, como el objetivo es extraordinario, los medios también deben serlo ("extraordinary"). No basta con ser "buenos cristianos" como lo eran en Inglaterra; deben hacer más. "we must entertaine each other in brotherly Affeccion" Afecto Fraternal: Deben tratarse como familia. Sacrificio Económico: Deben estar dispuestos a recortar sus propios excesos ("abridge our selves of our superfluities") para suplir las necesidades de los demás. "make others Condicions our owne rejoyce together" Empatía Total: La frase completa es "make others Condicions our owne, rejoyce together" (hacer nuestras las condiciones de los otros, regocijarnos juntos). Significa que si tu vecino sufre, tú debes sentir ese sufrimiento como propio; si él celebra, tú celebras. No hay indiferencia permitida.
<br>. . . wee must be knitt together in this worke as one man, we must entertaine each other in brotherly Affeccion, we must be willing to abridge our selves of our superfluities, for the suppy of others necessities, we must uphold a familiar Commerce together in meekenes, gentlenes, patience and liberallity, wee must delight in eache other, make others Condicions our owne rejoyce together, allwayes haveing before our eyes== our Commission and Community== in the worke. . . . for wee must Consider that wee shall be as a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity > ^3s4e3d" data-href="02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity#^3s4e3d" href="02.4_vocabulario-y-conceptos-históricos-winthrop-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html#^3s4e3d" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Citty upon a Hill</a> , the eies of all people are uppon us; soe that if wee shall deale falsely with our god in this worke wee have undertaken and soe cause him to withdrawe his present help from us, wee shall be made a story and a by-word through the world, we shall open the mouthes of enemies to speake evill of the wayes of god and all professours for Gods sake; wee shall shame the faces of many of gods worthy servants, and cause theire pra31yers to be turned into Curses upon us till we be consumed out of the good land whether we are going. . . .Summary "always haveing before our eyes our Commission and Community in the worke" Commission (La Comisión): Winthrop ve esto como un contrato legal con Dios. Dios les ha dado el permiso y los recursos para ir; ellos a cambio prometen construir una sociedad santa. El Riesgo: Si rompen el contrato ("deale falsely with our god"), Dios retirará su ayuda y perecerán. "wee shall be as a Citty upon a Hill, the eies of all people are uppon us" Esta es la conclusión famosa y terrible: Visibilidad Total: Ser una "Ciudad sobre una Colina" no es un premio, es una responsabilidad de alto riesgo. Significa que no pueden esconderse. El Juicio Mundial: "Los ojos de todos los pueblos están sobre nosotros". Si tienen éxito: Glorifican a Dios. Si fracasan: Se convertirán en una "historia y un refrán" (story and a by-word) de burla por todo el mundo. Avergonzarán a Dios y sus oraciones se convertirán en maldiciones hasta que sean "consumidos" (destruidos) de la tierra. Resumen: Winthrop les está diciendo: "Hemos firmado un contrato estricto con Dios. Si nos cuidamos unos a otros (amor fraternal) y ponemos a la comunidad primero, sobreviviremos y seremos un ejemplo. Si somos egoístas, todo el mundo nos verá fracasar y moriremos".Source: Edmund S. Morgan, ed., The Founding of Massachusetts: Historians and the Sources (Indianapolis, 1964).Additional Readings: David Grayson Allen, In English Ways: The Movement of Societies and the Transferal of English Local Law and Custom (Chapel Hill, 1981).David T. Konig, Law and Society in Puritan Massachusetts (1979)Perry Miller, Errand Into the Wilderness (Boston, 1956).__, The New England Mind: From Colony to Province (Boston, 1953).__, Orthodoxy in Massachusetts, 1630-1650 (New York, 1970).Edmund S. Morgan, Puritan Dilemma: The Story of John Winthrop (New York, 1958).Samuel Eliot Morison, Builders of the Bay Colony (Boston, 1930).Darrett Rutman, Winthrop's Boston (Chapel Hill, 1965). Winthrop Papers, multivolume (Boston, 1929 -).]]></description><link>02.3_winthrop,-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/02.3_Winthrop, John - A Model of Christian Charity.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 22:05:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity]]></title><description><![CDATA[Estos términos son esenciales para entender el contexto político, religioso y social del sermón de Winthrop.
Puritans (Puritanos): Grupo de protestantes ingleses de los siglos XVI y XVII que buscaban "purificar" la Iglesia de Inglaterra de prácticas católicas romanas. En el texto, se les describe como disidentes que buscaban alternativas a las instituciones establecidas. Gentry: Una clase social británica constituida por terratenientes acomodados ("caballeros") que estaban justo por debajo de la nobleza. Winthrop es descrito como un representante de la "new gentry" (nueva clase acomodada). Steward (Mayordomo/Administrador): En el contexto histórico, era el administrador financiero principal de una finca o mansión. En el contexto teológico del texto, Winthrop usa la metáfora de que los ricos son "God's Stewards" (Administradores de Dios), lo que significa que su riqueza no les pertenece, sino que la administran en nombre de Dios para ayudar a los pobres. Citty upon a Hill (Ciudad sobre una colina): Referencia bíblica (Mateo 5:14). Es la frase más famosa del documento. Significa que la colonia de Massachusetts estaría expuesta a la vista de todo el mundo y debía ser un modelo perfecto de caridad cristiana; si fallaban, serían una vergüenza mundial. Stuart Monarchy (Monarquía Estuardo): La casa real (Jacobo I, Carlos I) que gobernaba Inglaterra. Los puritanos, incluido Winthrop, se oponían a ellos por considerarlos corruptos y opresivos ("corrupt and oppressive"). Covenant (Pacto/Convenio): Aunque la palabra explícita usada a veces es "Commission" o "Bond", el concepto central es el Covenant. Es la idea de que el grupo tiene un contrato sagrado con Dios: si cumplen las reglas, prosperan; si no, son destruidos. El texto presenta una ortografía inestable (típica antes de la estandarización de los diccionarios en el s. XVIII).
Sufijos con "-e" muda: Es muy común ver una "e" extra al final de las palabras que hoy no existe. Ejemplos: woorke (work), owne (own), poore (poor), falsely (falsely - aquí se mantiene, pero en otras como greate), kind (kinde). Intercambio "i/y" y "u/v": Citty: City. Prividence: Providence (Providencia). Guifts: Gifts (regalos/dones). Terminaciones en "-cion" en lugar de "-tion": Condicion: Condition. Affecion: Affection. Corrupcions: Corruptions. Salvacion: Salvation. Abreviaturas numéricas: 2ly, 3ly, 4ly: Abreviatura de Secondly, Thirdly, Fourthly (En segundo lugar, etc.). Estas palabras existen hoy, pero Winthrop las usa con un significado diferente:
Meane (Mean): Hoy significa "malo/cruel" o "promedio". En este texto significa humilde, de bajo estatus social o pobre. Contexto: "...others meane and in subjection" (otros humildes y en sumisión). Ligament / Knit (Ligamento / Tejer o Unir): Winthrop usa una metáfora biológica y textil constante. La sociedad es un "cuerpo" y el amor es el "ligamento" que mantiene unidas las partes. Frase clave: "knitt together in this worke as one man" (unidos/tejidos en este trabajo como un solo hombre). Superfluities: Cosas superfluas. Se refiere al exceso de riqueza o lujos. Winthrop dice que los colonos deben sacrificar sus "superfluities" para ayudar a otros en necesidad. Professours (Professors): No significa "profesores académicos". En el siglo XVII, un professor era alguien que profesaba abiertamente su fe cristiana. Contexto: "...speake evill of the wayes of god and all professours" (hablar mal de los caminos de Dios y de todos los creyentes). Conversation / Commerce: En el texto se usa "Commerce together" y "Cohabitation". En este contexto, no se refiere solo a negocios, sino a la interacción social diaria y la convivencia entre vecinos. Errand: Usado en la introducción moderna ("errand into the wilderness"). Significa una misión o encargo con un propósito específico, no simplemente un "recado" trivial como se entiende hoy.
En la Página 4, Winthrop argumenta que una sociedad no es simplemente un grupo de individuos viviendo cerca, sino un organismo vivo.
El Problema de las Partes Sueltas: Winthrop explica que las partes de un cuerpo, consideradas por separado, son "desproporcionadas" y "caóticas" (disproportionate and as much disordering). Es decir, un individuo (rico o pobre) sin comunidad es inútil y monstruoso. El Amor como Ligamento: Aquí usa un término anatómico preciso para la época. Dice que el amor es un "ligamento" (ligament). En anatomía, los ligamentos unen los huesos y permiten el movimiento. Winthrop sostiene que sin este "ligamento de amor", el cuerpo social se deshace. No es un adorno sentimental, es la estructura que impide que la colonia se desmorone. Sensibilidad Compartida: La prueba de que este cuerpo funciona es la transmisión de sensaciones. Dice que las partes deben "participar mutuamente... tanto en fuerza y debilidad, en placer y dolor" (mutually participate... in strengthe and infirmity in pleasure and paine). Significado: Si el pobre sufre hambre, el rico debe sentir ese "dolor" físicamente. Si el rico ignora al pobre, el cuerpo está enfermo (paralizado o insensible). Esta es una de las imágenes más repetidas en el texto (aparece en las páginas 3, 4 y 5).
La Acción de Tejer: Winthrop repite que deben ser "knitt together" (tejidos juntos). La Unidad Absoluta: En la Página 5, la metáfora llega a su punto máximo cuando dice: "Wee must be knitt together in this worke as one man" (Debemos estar tejidos en este trabajo como un solo hombre). Ya no son "muchos colonos", son un solo hombre. Esto implica que la diversidad de clases (ricos/pobres) debe fundirse en una sola voluntad para sobrevivir. Winthrop aterriza estas metáforas religiosas en una regla política dura y pragmática en la Página 5:
"Particular estates cannott subsist in the ruine of the publique." (Los patrimonios particulares no pueden subsistir en la ruina de lo público). La Lógica: Usando la metáfora del cuerpo, explica que si el cuerpo muere (la colonia fracasa), el brazo (el individuo rico) también muere. Por lo tanto, el egoísmo no solo es pecado, es suicidio. La Regla de Oro: "The care of the publique must oversway all private respects" (El cuidado de lo público debe dominar sobre cualquier interés privado). Winthrop no estaba pidiendo "amabilidad". Estaba diseñando un sistema de supervivencia.
Anatomía: La sociedad es un cuerpo.
Fisiología: El amor es el ligamento y el sistema nervioso que conecta las partes.
Patología: El egoísmo es una enfermedad que corta los ligamentos; si ocurre, el cuerpo se desmiembra y muere.
Conclusión del sermón. Esta es la parte más dramática y famosa del texto, donde Winthrop deja de usar metáforas amables sobre el "cuerpo" y pasa a un lenguaje legal y apocalíptico de "vida o muerte".Winthrop plantea la migración no como un viaje, sino como un contrato estricto (Covenant) firmado con Dios.En la Página 6, Winthrop utiliza el término "Commission". En el lenguaje legal de la época, una "comisión" era un documento oficial que otorgaba autoridad para realizar una tarea específica, pero bajo condiciones estrictas.
Términos estrictos: Winthrop advierte que han hecho un pacto especial con Dios para esta misión. Dice: "If wee shall deale falsely with our god in this worke wee have undertaken..." (Si tratamos falsamente con nuestro Dios en este trabajo que hemos emprendido...). La Cláusula de Rescisión: Si fallan en cumplir su parte (vivir en caridad y unidad), Dios "withdrawe his present help from us" (retirará su ayuda presente de nosotros). Sin la protección divina activa, la colonia está condenada. Esta es la frase más célebre de todo el documento, pero a menudo se malinterpreta hoy en día como un símbolo de orgullo o superioridad. En el contexto de Winthrop (Página 6), era una advertencia sobre la visibilidad total y la presión extrema.
Escrutinio Público: "The eies of all people are uppon us" (Los ojos de toda la gente están sobre nosotros). El Riesgo de la Vergüenza: No dice "seremos un ejemplo brillante", sino que advierte que si fallan, la humillación será global. Ser una "ciudad sobre una colina" significa que no tienen dónde esconderse si fracasan. Winthrop detalla un castigo en tres niveles si rompen el pacto: Vergüenza Histórica: Dice que se convertirán en "a story and a by-word through the world" (una historia [de burla] y un refrán por todo el mundo). Un "by-word" es algo en lo que la gente piensa cuando quiere dar un ejemplo de fracaso. Es decir, se convertirían en el hazmerreír de la historia. Daño a la Fe: Su fracaso no solo los afectaría a ellos, sino a Dios. "We shall open the mouthes of enemies to speake evill of the wayes of god" (Abriremos las bocas de los enemigos para hablar mal de los caminos de Dios). Si los puritanos fracasan, sus enemigos en Inglaterra y la Iglesia Católica dirán: "¿Vieron? Su religión era falsa". Destrucción Física: La advertencia final es la extinción: "Till we be consumed out of the good land whether we are going" (Hasta que seamos consumidos [eliminados] de la buena tierra a la que vamos). Winthrop está diciendo literalmente: si no cuidamos los unos de los otros, moriremos en este desierto. El argumento de Winthrop es que la caridad no es una opción moral extra, sino un mecanismo de supervivencia política.
Si se mantienen unidos ("knitt together"), Dios garantiza el éxito. Si se dividen por egoísmo, rompen la "Comisión" y enfrentan la destrucción total.
]]></description><link>02.4_vocabulario-y-conceptos-históricos-winthrop-john-a-model-of-christian-charity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/02.4_Vocabulario y Conceptos Históricos - Winthrop John - A Model of Christian Charity.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 21:48:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[02.1_Frethorne, Richard - Letter to His Parents]]></title><description><![CDATA[
[...] colonization in the early seventeenth century. Combatting homesickness, disease, hunger, discomfort, and isolation, Frethorne and his fellow settlers struggled to make a success of their fledgling community. As might be expected, many longed to be "redeemed out of Egypt" and return to their former lives across the Atlantic. Frethorne's correspondence reveals the poignancy of the struggle for survival waged by the class of indentured servants in the new world.
— Lisbeth Cohen, Montana State University
Loving and kind father and mother:My most humble duty remembered to you, hoping in God of your good health, as I myself am at the making hereof. This is to let you understand that I your child am in a most heavy case by reason of the nature of the country, [which] is such that it causeth much sickness, as the scurvy and the bloody flux and diverse other diseases, which maketh the body very poor and weak. And when we are sick there is nothing to comfort us; for since I came out of the ship I never ate anything but peas, and loblollie (that is, water gruel). As for deer or venison I never saw any since I came into this land. There is indeed some fowl, but we are not allowed to go and get it, but must work hard both early and late for a mess of water gruel and a mouthful of bread and beef. A mouthful of bread for a penny loaf must serve for four men which is most pitiful....People cry out day and night—Oh! that they were in England without their limbs—and would not care to lose any limb to be England again, yea, though they beg from door to door. For we live in fear of the enemy every hour, yet we have had a combat with them on the Sunday before Shrovetide,^1 and we took two alive and made slaves of them. But it was by policy, for we are in great danger; for our plantation is very weak by reason of the death and sickness of our company. For we came but twenty for the merchants, and they are half dead just; and we look every hour when two more should go. Yet there came some four other men yet to live with us, of which there is but one alive; and our Lieutenant is dead, and his father and his brother. And there was some five or six of the last year’s twenty, of which there is but three left, so that we are fain to get other men to plant with us; and yet we are but 32 to fight against 3000 if they should come. And the nighest help that we have is ten miles of us, and when the rogues overcame this place last they slew 80 persons. How then shall we do, for we lie even in their teeth? They may easily take us, but that God is merciful and can save with few as well as with many, as he showed to Gilead.^2 ...And I have nothing to comfort me, nor there is nothing to be gotten here but sickness and death, except that one had money to lay out in some things for profit. But I have nothing at all—no, not a shirt to my back but two rags (2), nor no clothes but one poor suit, nor but one pair of shoes, but one pair of stockings, but one cap, but two bands. My cloak is stolen by one of my own fellows, and to his dying hour [he] would not tell me what he did with it; but some of my fellows saw him have butter and beef out of a ship, which my cloak, I doubt [not], paid for. So that I have not a penny, nor a penny worth, to help me to either spice or sugar or strong waters, without the which one cannot live here. For as strong beer in1 England doth fatten and strengthen them, so water here doth wash and weaken these here [and] only keeps life and soul together. 2But I am not half a quarter so strong as I was in England, and all is for want of victuals; for I do protest unto you that I have eaten more in [one] day at home than I have allowed me here for a week. You have given more than my day’s allowance to a beggar at the door: and if Mr. Jackson had not relieved me, I should be in a poor case. But he like a father and she like a loving mother doth still help me.3...Goodman Jackson pitied me and made me a cabin to lie in... which comforted me more than peas or water gruel. Oh, they be very godly folks, and love me very well, and will do anything for me. And he much marvelled that you would send me a servant to the Company; he saith I had been better knocked on the head. And indeed so I find it now, to my great grief and misery; and saith that if you love me you will redeem me suddenly, for which I do entreat and beg. And if you cannot get the merchants to redeem me for some little money, then for God’s sake get a gathering or entreat some good folks to lay out some little sum of money in meal and cheese and butter and beef. Any eating meat will yield great profit. Oil and vinegar is very good; but, father, there is great loss in leaking. But for God’s sake send beef and cheese and butter, or the more of one sort and none of another. But if you send cheese, it must be very old cheese; and at the cheesemonger’s you may buy very good cheese for two pence farthing or halfpenny, that will be liked very well. But if you send cheese, you must have a care how you pack it in barrels; and you must put cooper’s chips between every cheese, or else the heat of the hold will rot them. And look whatsoever you send me—be it never so much—look, what[ever] I make of it, I will deal truly with you. I will send it over and beg the profit to redeem me; and if I die before it come, I have entreated Goodman Jackson to send you the worth of it, who hath promised he will....ExplicaciónEsta es una de las partes más conmovedoras y reveladoras de la carta. Aquí, Richard Frethorne deja de lado las descripciones generales de la colonia para hablar de su estrategia personal de supervivencia y lanzar una súplica desesperada (y manipuladora) a sus padres.
Aquí te explico los puntos clave de este fragmento desglosados por temas: Frethorne introduce a un tal Sr. Jackson (Goodman era un título para hombres respetables pero no nobles). El contraste: Mientras sus propios padres lo enviaron a sufrir, este extraño lo "compadeció" (pitied me), le construyó una cabaña y lo trató como a un hijo. La crítica indirecta: Frethorne usa a Jackson para criticar a sus padres sin hacerlo directamente. Dice que Jackson "se maravilló" de que sus padres lo hubieran enviado como sirviente y dijo que "habría sido mejor que me golpearan en la cabeza" (better knocked on the head). Es una forma brutal de decir: "Enviarme aquí fue una sentencia de muerte, y hasta un extraño se da cuenta". La palabra clave aquí es "Redeem" (Redimir/Rescatar). Frethorne quiere romper su contrato de servidumbre (indenture). Plan A: Pide a sus padres que paguen directamente a los comerciantes para cancelar su contrato. Plan B (Comercio): Si no tienen dinero ("if you cannot get the merchants to redeem me"), les propone un negocio. Les pide que hagan una colecta (get a gathering) entre vecinos para comprar comida (carne, queso, mantequilla) y enviársela a Virginia. Frethorne no solo pide comida para alimentarse, la pide para venderla. Dice: "Any eating meat will yield great profit" (Cualquier carne comestible dará gran beneficio). En la Virginia de 1623, la comida escaseaba tanto que valía mucho más que el dinero. Su plan es recibir esa comida, venderla en la colonia y usar las ganancias (profit) para comprar su propia libertad. Es fascinante ver cómo Frethorne da instrucciones muy técnicas sobre cómo enviar la mercancía, lo que demuestra lo difícil que era el transporte transatlántico: El queso: Debe ser "very old cheese" (queso muy curado) para que aguante el viaje. El embalaje: Les instruye poner "cooper’s chips" (virutas de madera de tonelero) entre cada queso. La razón: Si no lo hacen, el calor de la bodega del barco (the heat of the hold) hará que se pudran (rot). El párrafo termina con una nota muy oscura que refleja la realidad de la mortalidad en la colonia: Frethorne promete ser honesto con las ganancias (deal truly with you). Pero añade: "y si muero antes de que llegue [la comida]". Ha dejado instrucciones a Goodman Jackson para que, si Richard muere antes de que llegue el envío, Jackson venda la comida y devuelva el dinero a los padres en Inglaterra. Esto demuestra que Frethorne sabe que la muerte es inminente. En resumen: Este párrafo es un grito de auxilio disfrazado de plan de negocios. Frethorne les está diciendo a sus padres: "Me equivoqué al venir, un extraño me cuida mejor que ustedes, envíenme mercancía para comprar mi libertad o moriré aquí pronto".Good father, do not forget me, but have mercy and pity my miserable case. I know if you did but see me, you would weep to see me; for I have but one suit.... Wherefore, for God’s sake, pity me. I pray you to remember my love to all my friends and kindred. I hope all my brothers and sisters are in good health, and as for my part I have set down my resolution that certainly will be; that is, that the answer of this letter will be life or death to me. Therefore good father, send as soon as you can; and if you send me any thing let this be the mark.ROTRichard Frethorne,Martin's HundredAll these died out of my master’s house, since I came; and we came in but at Christmas, and this is the 20th day of March. And the sailors say that there is two-thirds of the 150 dead already. And thus I end, praying to God to send me good success that I may be redeemed out of Egypt. So vale in Christo.Loving father, I pray you to use this man very exceeding kindly, for he hath done much for me, both on my journey and since. I entreat you not to forget me, but by any means redeem me; for this day we hear that there is 26 of Englishmen slain by the Indians. And they have taken a pinnace of Mr. Pountis, and have gotten pieces, armor, swords, all things fit for war; so that they may now steal upon us and we cannot know them from English till it is too late—that they be upon us—and then there is no mercy. Therefore if you love or respect me as your child, release me from the bondage and save my life. Now you may save me, or let me be slain with infidels. Ask this man—he knoweth that all is true and just that I say here. If you do redeem me, the Company must send for me to my Mr. Harrod; for so is this Master’s name. April, the second day.Your loving son,Richard FrethorneMoreover, on the third day of April we heard that after these rogues had gotten the pinnace and had taken all furnitures [such] as pieces, swords, armor, coats of mail, powder, shot and all the things that they had to trade withal, they killed the Captain and cut off his head. And rowing with the tail of the boat foremost, they set up a pole and put the Captain’s head upon it, and so rowed home. Then the Devil set them on again, so that they furnished about 200 canoes with above 1000 Indians, and came, and thought to have taken the ship; but she was too quick for them—which thing was very much talked of, for they always feared a ship. But now the rogues grow very bold and can use pieces, some of them, as well or better than an Englishman; for an Indian did shoot with Mr. Charles, my master’s kinsman, at a mark of white paper, and he hit it at the first, but Mr. Charles could not hit it. But see the envy of these slaves, for when they could not take the ship, then our men saw them threaten Accomack, that is the next plantation. And now there is no way but starving: . . . For they had no crop last year by reason of these rogues, so that we have no corn but as ships do relieve us, nor we shall hardly have any crop this year; and we are as like to perish first as any plantation. For we have but two hogsheads of meal left to serve us this two months, . . . that is but a halfpennyloaf a day for a man. Is it not strange to me, think you? But what will it be when we shall go a month or two and never see a bit of bread, as my master doth say we must do? And he said he is not able to keep us all. Then we shall be turned up to the land and eat barks of trees or molds of the ground; therefore with weeping tears I beg of you to help me. Oh, that you did see my daily and hourly sighs, groans, and tears, and thumps that I afford mine own breast, and rue and curse the time of my birth, with holy Job. I thought no head had been able to hold so much water as hath and doth daily flow from mine eyes.But this is certain: I never felt the want of father and mother till now; but now, dear friends, full well I know and rue it, although it were too late before I knew it....Your loving son,Richard FrethorneVirginia, 3rd April, ExplicaciónEste fragmento es la conclusión de la carta y constituye la parte más dramática y desesperada. Aquí Frethorne narra el colapso total de la seguridad en la colonia debido a la guerra con los nativos y la hambruna inminente.
Aquí te explico los puntos clave que están ocurriendo en este texto: Frethorne comienza actualizando el recuento de bajas. El dato: Llegaron en Navidad con 150 personas. Para el 20 de marzo, los marineros estiman que dos tercios ya han muerto. "Redeemed out of Egypt": Frethorne usa una metáfora bíblica. Compara su situación en Virginia con la esclavitud de los israelitas en el Egipto faraónico. Pedir ser "redimido de Egipto" significa ser rescatado de la esclavitud y la muerte. El 2 de abril y el 3 de abril, la situación empeora drásticamente. El robo estratégico: Los nativos (a los que llama "rogues" o bribones) capturaron una pinaza (un barco pequeño de exploración) perteneciente al Sr. Pountis. Con el barco, consiguieron un arsenal: armaduras, espadas, pólvora y armas de fuego. Guerra psicológica: Frethorne relata una escena de terror. Los nativos mataron al Capitán, le cortaron la cabeza y la pusieron en un poste en el barco capturado, remando con la popa hacia adelante para exhibir el trofeo mientras regresaban a su territorio. El ataque masivo: Envalentonados, reunieron 200 canoas y 1000 guerreros para intentar capturar el barco principal, aunque no lo lograron. Esta es quizás la parte que más miedo le da a Frethorne. Adaptación indígena: Los colonos dependían de sus armas de fuego ("pieces") para mantener la ventaja. Sin embargo, Frethorne admite que ahora los nativos "se han vuelto muy audaces y pueden usar las armas... tan bien o mejor que un inglés". La prueba: Cuenta una anécdota humillante donde un nativo compitió disparando a un blanco de papel contra el Sr. Charles (pariente del amo de Frethorne). El nativo acertó al primer intento, mientras que el inglés falló. Esto significaba que los colonos ya no estaban seguros ni siquiera con sus mosquetes. Debido a la guerra, no pudieron plantar cultivos el año anterior y no pueden plantar este año porque los nativos los acechan. Raciones: Solo quedan dos barriles (hogsheads) de harina para dos meses. Eso equivale a medio panecillo ("halfpenny loaf") al día por persona. Medidas desesperadas: Su amo ha admitido que no puede mantenerlos a todos. Frethorne anticipa que pronto los echarán al campo a comer "cortezas de árboles o moho de la tierra" (barks of trees or molds of the ground). El texto termina con Frethorne llorando, golpeándose el pecho y maldiciendo el momento de su nacimiento, comparándose con el Santo Job (figura bíblica que lo perdió todo y sufrió plagas). Termina con una confesión desgarradora: nunca valoró a sus padres hasta ahora, cuando ya es demasiado tarde.
En resumen, este fragmento explica por qué la carta es tan urgente: no se trata solo de trabajo duro, se enfrentan a un enemigo que ha aprendido a usar sus propias armas y a una hambruna que los obligará a comer tierra.**Footnotes:
Shrovetide: The three days before Ash Wednesday, former76ly set aside as a period of confession and a time of festivity preceding Lent in Christian77 practice.
Gilead: A region east of the Jordan River settled in biblical times by, among others, Is87raelites who were successfully defended in battle against vastly superior numbers of invaders by Judas Maccabeus and his warriors.
Pinnace: A small sailing boat, often used as a scout for a larger vessel.
]]></description><link>02.1_frethorne,-richard-letter-to-his-parents.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/02.1_Frethorne, Richard - Letter to His Parents.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 22:02:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[02.2_Vocabulario Histórico - Frethorne - Letter to his Parents]]></title><description><![CDATA[vocabulario histórico clave extraído de los textos de Richard Frethorne y Thomas Morton. He organizado los términos por categorías para facilitar su comprensión, incluyendo el término original en inglés, su traducción aproximada y el contexto histórico específico.Estos términos aparecen principalmente en la carta de Frethorne y reflejan las duras condiciones de Virginia.
Bloody flux (Flujo sangriento): Un término histórico para la disentería, una enfermedad intestinal grave que causaba diarrea con sangre. Era una de las principales causas de muerte en las colonias. Scurvy (Escorbuto): Enfermedad causada por la deficiencia de vitamina C, común entre marineros y colonos debido a la falta de frutas y verduras frescas. Loblollie / Water gruel (Gachas aguadas): Una papilla muy líquida y sin sustancia hecha de agua y granos (avena o maíz). Frethorne se queja de que esto es lo único que comen. Victuals (Vituallas/Provisiones): Alimentos o provisiones necesarias para la vida. Hogsheads (Bocoyes): Barriles grandes utilizados para transportar mercancías (tabaco, harina, líquidos). Frethorne menciona que solo les quedan dos "hogsheads" de harina. Conceptos clave para entender la jerarquía en la colonia.
Indentured servant (Sirviente contratado/por contrato): Aunque no aparece la frase exacta en el texto, el contexto describe esta condición. Eran personas que firmaban un contrato trabajando gratis durante años (generalmente 4-7) a cambio del pasaje a América, comida y alojamiento. Frethorne es uno de ellos. Goodman: Un título de cortesía utilizado para dirigirse a un hombre de posición social respetable, pero inferior a la de un caballero ("Gentleman" o "Mr."). Ejemplo: "Goodman Jackson". Fellows (Compañeros): En este contexto, se refiere a otros sirvientes o trabajadores del mismo rango que Frethorne. Redeem (Redimir/Rescatar): Frethorne ruega a sus padres que lo "rediman", es decir, que paguen su contrato para liberarlo de su servidumbre antes de tiempo. Pinnace (Pinaza): Una embarcación de vela ligera, utilizada a menudo como exploradora para barcos más grandes o para navegar en aguas poco profundas (ríos y bahías). Pieces (Piezas/Armas de fuego): Se refiere a mosquetes o armas de fuego ("fowling pieces"). Frethorne menciona que los nativos han conseguido "pieces". Shot (Perdigones/Munición): Proyectiles para las armas de fuego. Cooper’s chips (Virutas de tonelero): Astillas de madera utilizadas para rellenar espacios vacíos en los barriles y evitar que el contenido (como el queso) se pudriera por el calor o la humedad. Estos términos son más relevantes en la sección sobre Thomas Morton y el conflicto en Nueva Inglaterra.
Separatist (Separatista): Puritanos radicales (como los Peregrinos de Plymouth) que deseaban separarse completamente de la Iglesia de Inglaterra, a diferencia de otros puritanos que querían reformarla desde dentro. Puritan (Puritano): Grupo protestante inglés que buscaba "purificar" la Iglesia de Inglaterra de prácticas católicas. Eran conocidos por su rigidez moral. Maypole (Palo de mayo): Un poste alto decorado con flores y cintas, centro de festividades folclóricas tradicionales inglesas. Los puritanos lo consideraban una práctica pagana e inmoral (Morton erigió uno en Merry-mount). Shrovetide (Carnestolendas): Los tres días previos al Miércoles de Ceniza (inicio de la Cuaresma). Era una época tradicional de festejos que Frethorne menciona como fecha de un combate. Rogues (Bribones/Pícaros): Frethorne usa este término de manera despectiva para referirse a los nativos americanos. Betwixt (Entre): Forma arcaica de "between". Fain (Dispuesto/Obligado): Estar dispuesto a hacer algo por necesidad ("we are fain to get other men"). Panegyric (Panegírico): Un discurso o texto de alabanza excesiva (mencionado en el análisis literario sobre Morton).
]]></description><link>02.2_vocabulario-histórico-frethorne-letter-to-his-parents.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/02.2_Vocabulario Histórico - Frethorne - Letter to his Parents.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:33:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[C_Evolución de la Identidad Americana]]></title><description><![CDATA[Etiquetas: <a href=".?query=tag:identidad" class="tag is-unresolved" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow" data-href="#identidad">#identidad</a> <a href=".?query=tag:examen_final" class="tag is-unresolved" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow" data-href="#examen_final">#examen_final</a> <a href=".?query=tag:comparativa" class="tag is-unresolved" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow" data-href="#comparativa">#comparativa</a><br>
Links: <a data-href="Winthrop_A_Model_of_Christian_Charity" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Winthrop_A_Model_of_Christian_Charity</a> | <a data-href="Crevecoeur_What_is_an_American" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Crevecoeur_What_is_an_American</a>La identidad americana evoluciona desde una misión colectiva y religiosa excluyente en el siglo XVII (Puritanos) hacia una identidad individualista, secular y agraria en el siglo XVIII (Ilustración).
<br><a data-href="Winthrop_A_Model_of_Christian_Charity" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Winthrop_A_Model_of_Christian_Charity</a> (1630): La unión se basa en un pacto religioso ("Covenant"). La comunidad es como un cuerpo donde cada parte debe ayudarse por amor cristiano ("ligaments of love"). [cite_start]La desigualdad es natural y deseada por Dios para fomentar la caridad[cite: 96].
<br><a data-href="Crevecoeur_What_is_an_American" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Crevecoeur_What_is_an_American</a> (1782): La unión se basa en el interés propio y el trabajo. El "americano" deja atrás sus antiguos prejuicios y costumbres europeos para abrazar una nueva vida basada en la industria y la recompensa económica. [cite_start]No es la religión lo que une, sino la ley y la oportunidad[cite: 156]. Winthrop: "City upon a Hill" (La Ciudad en la Colina). Una posición defensiva, estática y vigilada por el mundo. El miedo al fracaso ante Dios es central.
Crevecoeur: "The Melting Pot" (aunque no usa el término exacto, describe la mezcla). "Here individuals of all nations are melted into a new race of men". Es una imagen dinámica, biológica y expansiva. Visión Puritana: Solo los "elegidos" o santos visibles. Es altamente excluyente (ej. expulsión de Anne Hutchinson o Roger Williams).
<br>Visión de Crevecoeur: Cualquiera (europeo) que trabaje la tierra. [cite_start]Es inclusiva en términos de nacionalidad europea ("a mixture of English, Scotch, Irish, French, Dutch..."), pero ignora la realidad de los nativos y esclavos que <a data-href="Freneau_The_Indian_Burying_Ground" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Freneau_The_Indian_Burying_Ground</a> [cite: 171] [cite_start]o <a data-href="Wheatley_On_Being_Brought" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Wheatley_On_Being_Brought</a> [cite: 102] denunciarían después.
Mientras Winthrop define América como un experimento moral bajo juicio divino, Crevecoeur la redefine como un refugio económico y social. Este cambio marca la transición del pensamiento teocéntrico colonial al pensamiento antropocéntrico de la Revolución.]]></description><link>c_evolución-de-la-identidad-americana.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/C_Evolución de la Identidad Americana.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:06:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[00_Final]]></title><description><![CDATA[Meta: Examen Final Febrero 2025
Programa: <a data-href="Programa_2025" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Programa_2025</a><br>
Tema Especial (Oral): <a data-href="Tema_Seleccionado" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Tema_Seleccionado</a>
Unidades:<br>
<a data-href="Unidad_1_Encuentro_de_Culturas" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_1_Encuentro_de_Culturas</a><br>
<a data-href="Unidad_2_Tiempos_Coloniales" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_2_Tiempos_Coloniales</a><br>
<a data-href="Unidad_3_Siglo_XVIII" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_3_Siglo_XVIII</a><br>
<a data-href="Unidad_4_Siglo_XIX" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_4_Siglo_XIX</a><br>
<a data-href="Unidad_5_Siglos_XX_XXI" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_5_Siglos_XX_XXI</a>]]></description><link>00_final.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Cultura/00_Final.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:05:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[abridge]]></title><description><![CDATA[To deprive; to cut off.
He had his rights abridged by the crooked sheriff.
]]></description><link>definitions/abridge.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/abridge.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 21:46:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[fledgling]]></title><description><![CDATA[a person or organization that is immature, inexperienced, or underdeveloped.]]></description><link>definitions/fledgling.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/fledgling.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 21:40:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Definiciones Cultura]]></title><link>definitions/definiciones-cultura.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Definiciones Cultura.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 21:39:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Meane]]></title><description><![CDATA[Hoy significa "malo/cruel" o "promedio". En este texto significa humilde, de bajo estatus social o pobre.]]></description><link>definitions/meane.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Meane.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 21:32:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Forth (en-GB)]]></title><description><![CDATA[
/fɔːθ/ /fɔɹθ/ Forward in time, place or degree.Out into view; from a particular place or position.
The plants in spring put forth leaves.
Beyond a (certain) boundary; away; abroad; out.Thoroughly; from beginning to end.Forth from; out of.]]></description><link>definitions/forth-(en-gb).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Forth (en-GB).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 22:14:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Shew (en-GB)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ /ʃəʊ/ /ʃoʊ/
A play, dance, or other entertainment.An exhibition of items.
art show;&nbsp; dog show
A broadcast program/programme.
radio show;&nbsp; television show
A movie.
Let's catch a show.
An agricultural show.
I'm taking the kids to the show on Tuesday.
A project or presentation.
Let's get on with the show.&nbsp;&nbsp; Let's get this show on the road.&nbsp;&nbsp; They went on an international road show to sell the shares to investors.&nbsp;&nbsp; It was Apple's usual dog and pony show.
A demonstration.
show of force
Mere display or pomp with no substance. (Usually seen in the phrases "all show" and "for show".)
The dog sounds ferocious but it's all show.
Outward appearance; wileful or deceptive appearance.(with "the") The major leagues.
He played AA ball for years, but never made it to the show.
A pale blue flame at the top of a candle flame, indicating the presence of firedamp.Pretence.Sign, token, or indication.Semblance; likeness; appearance.Plausibility.A discharge, from the vagina, of mucus streaked with blood, occurring a short time before labor.To display, to have somebody see (something).
All he had to show for four years of attendance at college was a framed piece of paper.
To bestow; to confer.To indicate (a fact) to be true; to demonstrate.To guide or escort.
Could you please show him on his way. He has overstayed his welcome.
To be visible; to be seen; to appear.
At length, his gloom showed.
To put in an appearance; show up.
We waited for an hour, but they never showed.
To have an enlarged belly and thus be recognizable as pregnant.(racing) To finish third, especially of horses or dogs.
In the third race: Aces Up won, paying eight dollars; Blarney Stone placed, paying three dollars; and Cinnamon showed, paying five dollars.
To have a certain appearance, such as well or ill, fit or unfit; to become or suit; to appear.]]></description><link>definitions/shew-(en-gb).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Shew (en-GB).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 22:13:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Endowed (en-GB)]]></title><description><![CDATA[
/ɪnˈdaʊd/
To provide with a dower or a dowry.To give property to (someone) as a gift; specifically, to provide (a person or institution) with support in the form of a permanent fund of money or other benefits.Followed by with, or rarely by of: to enrich or furnish with some faculty or quality.begiftUsually in the passive: to naturally furnish (with something).
She was endowed with a beautiful voice.
bless, giftProvided or furnished with something.Founded by an endowment.]]></description><link>definitions/endowed-(en-gb).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Endowed (en-GB).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 22:08:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fowl (en-GB)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ /faʊl/ A bird.A bird of the order Galliformes, including chickens, turkeys, pheasant, partridges and quail.Birds which are hunted or kept for food, including Galliformes and also waterfowl of the order Anseriformes such as ducks, geese and swans.To hunt fowl.
We took our guns and went fowling.
]]></description><link>definitions/fowl-(en-gb).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Fowl (en-GB).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:47:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[scurvy]]></title><description><![CDATA[ (Escorbuto): Enfermedad causada por la deficiencia de vitamina C, común entre marineros y colonos debido a la falta de frutas y verduras frescas.]]></description><link>definitions/scurvy.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/scurvy.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:46:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[bloody flux]]></title><description><![CDATA[Un término histórico para la disentería, una enfermedad intestinal grave que causaba diarrea con sangre. Era una de las principales causas de muerte en las colonias.]]></description><link>definitions/bloody-flux.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/bloody flux.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:45:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hereof (en-GB)]]></title><description><![CDATA[Of this; concerning this.From or as a result of this.]]></description><link>definitions/hereof-(en-gb).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Hereof (en-GB).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:43:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Poignancy (en-GB)]]></title><description><![CDATA[
'pɔɪnjənsɪ
ˈpɔɪnjənsɪ
Poignancy is the quality that something has when it affects you deeply and makes you feel very sad.&nbsp; The film contains moments of almost unbearable poignancy...
]]></description><link>definitions/poignancy-(en-gb).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Poignancy (en-GB).md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 20:41:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Nota Cultura]]></title><description><![CDATA[Autor: <a data-href="Nombre Autor" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Nombre Autor</a>
Año: Año<br>
Unidad: <a data-href="Unidad_X" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unidad_X</a><br>
Tags: <a href=".?query=tag:historia" class="tag is-unresolved" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow" data-href="#historia">#historia</a> <a href=".?query=tag:literatura" class="tag is-unresolved" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow" data-href="#literatura">#literatura</a> <a href=".?query=tag:cultura" class="tag is-unresolved" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow" data-href="#cultura">#cultura</a> <a href=".?query=tag:identidad" class="tag is-unresolved" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow" data-href="#identidad">#identidad</a>(Escribe aquí en una o dos oraciones el argumento central del autor).
Concepto 1
Concepto 2 Cita textual o paráfrasis importante.
Conexión con el contexto histórico. <br>Se relaciona con <a data-href="Otro_Texto" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Otro_Texto</a> por...
<br>Contrasta con <a data-href="Autor_Y" href=".html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Autor_Y</a> en... ]]></description><link>template/nota-cultura.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Template/Nota Cultura.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 16:20:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cabrilo Mercum]]></title><description><![CDATA[Crear un regalo
Crear un NPCCollar de un martillo de guerra grabado sobre un escudo. Detras del escudo tiene varias iniciales grabadas de compañeros cercanos a Cabrilo.
Dado por una vieja compañera de cuartel llamada Merim en dónde hice mi entrenamiento militar. Ella lo mandó a hacer al herrero del pueblo.Edad: 25
Raza: Humana
Relación: amistad/hermandad
Empezamos los dos como iniciados en el cuartel de guerra "La Aguja del Amanecer". A pesar de yo ser dos años mayor que ella, su actitud protectora terminó poniendo a Camilo (Ahora Cabrilo) en el rol de hermano menor.
Aspectos:
Forma de hablar: no tiene miedo en decir lo que piensa. En ocasiones, su forma de expresarse es tosca y no condice con lo que siente.
Físico: Una humana de pelo rojo escarlata hasta los hombros. Merim tiene una contextura física marcada por tantos años de entrenamiento. Mide alrededor de 1.80. ]]></description><link>rpg/pathfinder/estamos-contratando/cabrilo-mercum.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">RPG/Pathfinder/Estamos Contratando/Cabrilo Mercum.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 15:24:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Herramientas para el Ensayo Reflexivo]]></title><description><![CDATA[Esta tabla organiza frases y preguntas guía según la estructura de un ensayo y los pasos de la escritura reflexiva.Estas preguntas se basan en los cuatro pasos del ciclo de escritura reflexiva para ayudarte a profundizar en tus ideas.
¿Qué escenas o citas específicas de Cathal interactuando con Sabene, o recordando a su padre, demuestran mejor su misoginia interiorizada?
¿Qué palabras exactas usa él (o los demás) que te llamaron la atención?
¿Cómo describe Keegan el ambiente o la tensión en esos momentos? Al leer esa escena, ¿qué sentí exactamente? ¿Frustración, tristeza, reconocimiento?
¿Por qué esta situación en particular me hizo pensar en mi propia experiencia con mi padre? ¿Qué similitudes o diferencias veo?
¿Qué me dice esta reacción emocional sobre mis propios valores o creencias? ¿Qué patrón de comportamiento estoy identificando en Cathal? ¿Cómo se conecta su pasado con sus acciones presentes?
¿Qué tema más amplio emerge de mi reflexión? (Por ejemplo: la ceguera ante el privilegio, la comunicación fallida, la perpetuación de roles de género).
¿Cómo usa Keegan el personaje de Cathal para criticar una idea más grande sobre la sociedad? ¿Cuál creo que es el mensaje central que Claire Keegan intenta transmitir sobre la misoginia y la soledad?
Si tuviera que resumir la "lección" de la novela en una sola frase, ¿cuál sería?
Después de esta reflexión, ¿mi forma de ver este tema ha cambiado o se ha reforzado? ¿De qué manera?
Estas herramientas están diseñadas para ayudarte a organizar tus pensamientos y a expresarlos de una manera que sea a la vez personal y analítica.Ahora que tienes estas herramientas, ¿te sientes más preparado/a para empezar a redactar el primer párrafo de tu ensayo?]]></description><link>universidad/literature-ii/herramientas-para-el-ensayo-reflexivo.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/Herramientas para el Ensayo Reflexivo.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:18:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sueños y Pensamientos 2]]></title><link>sueños-y-pensamientos/sueños-y-pensamientos-2.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sueños y Pensamientos/Sueños y Pensamientos 2.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 08:06:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sueños y Pensamientos 1]]></title><link>sueños-y-pensamientos/sueños-y-pensamientos-1.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sueños y Pensamientos/Sueños y Pensamientos 1.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 08:06:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Sueños y Pensamientos]]></title><link>sueños-y-pensamientos/sueños-y-pensamientos.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Sueños y Pensamientos/Sueños y Pensamientos.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 07:02:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Vampiro]]></title><link>vampiro/vampiro.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Vampiro/Vampiro.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 22:26:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[PE 3]]></title><link>universidad/pe-3/pe-3.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/PE 3/PE 3.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 22:25:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Adquisición]]></title><link>universidad/adquisición/adquisición.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Adquisición/Adquisición.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Oct 2025 22:24:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Plano para un Ensayo Reflexivo Literario]]></title><description><![CDATA[Propósito: Captar la atención del lector, presentar el tema y establecer tu punto de vista reflexivo.
Contexto (1 oración): Presenta la obra, el autor y el tema que has elegido (p. ej., Desconexión, Soledad, etc.). Ejemplo: "In her novel So Late in the Day, Claire Keegan masterfully explores the theme of disconnection within modern relationships." Tesis Reflexiva (1-2 oraciones): Esta es tu idea principal y tu "hilo dorado". Conecta el tema del libro con un aprendizaje o una reflexión personal. Fórmula de ejemplo: "Exploring [TEMA] in the novel prompted me to reflect on how [TU APRENDIZAJE O CONEXIÓN PERSONAL]."
Ejemplo: "Exploring this theme prompted me to reflect on how unspoken expectations can become the most significant barriers to genuine human connection." Propósito: Desarrollar tu tesis reflexiva usando el ciclo "Qué, Porqué y Cómo". Aquí es donde conectas el texto con tu experiencia.
Oración Temática (1 oración): Empieza el párrafo conectando una idea específica del libro con tu tesis. Ejemplo: "The suffocating silence during the couple's final car ride serves as a powerful symbol of their emotional distance." Descripción - "El Qué" (1-2 oraciones): Describe brevemente la escena o cita del libro que vas a usar como evidencia. Sé conciso, no resumas la trama. Ejemplo: "Keegan describes not a heated argument, but a quiet, tense atmosphere where what is left unsaid is more significant than any conversation." Evaluación y Análisis - "El Porqué / Y qué?" (3-4 oraciones): Aquí ocurre la reflexión. Explica por qué esta escena te impactó. Conéctala con tus propias ideas, sentimientos u observaciones. Esta es tu respuesta a la pregunta: "¿Y qué?". Ejemplo: "This resonated with my own understanding of passive conflict. It made me realize that the absence of fighting does not equate to peace; instead, it can signify a deeper resignation. It challenged my belief that avoiding difficult conversations is a way to preserve a relationship." Síntesis - "El Cómo / El Aprendizaje" (1-2 oraciones): Cierra el párrafo con la conclusión o el aprendizaje que extraes de este análisis. ¿Qué idea más amplia has generado? Ejemplo: "Therefore, I've come to understand that genuine connection requires the courage to face discomfort, a lesson Cathal learns far too late." Propósito: Resumir tu reflexión principal y dejar al lector con una idea final clara.
Reafirmación de la Reflexión (1 oración): Vuelve a enunciar tu tesis con otras palabras, ahora reforzada por tu análisis. Ejemplo: "Ultimately, Keegan's narrative served as a poignant reminder that emotional disconnection is not a sudden event, but a gradual erosion caused by fear and unspoken truths." Mirada al Futuro (1 oración): Termina con una breve reflexión sobre cómo esta nueva comprensión podría influir en tu perspectiva o acciones futuras. Ejemplo: "This insight encourages me to approach my own relationships with greater honesty and communicative vulnerability." Usa conectores para unir estos bloques de forma fluida. Palabras como Furthermore, This scene reveals..., Consequently, y This resonated with me because... actuarán como el cemento que une los ladrillos de tu estructura.]]></description><link>universidad/literature-ii/plano-para-un-ensayo-reflexivo-literario.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/Plano para un Ensayo Reflexivo Literario.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 15:54:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>universidad/literature-ii/mla-quotations.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/MLA Quotations.md</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>universidad/literature-ii/untitled.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/Untitled.md</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[So Late in the Day]]></title><description><![CDATA[Quote
His mother had served everyone, brought their plates to the table, and they had begun to eat. When she went to sit down, with her own plate, his brother had reached out and quickly pulled the chair from under her – and she had fallen backwards, onto the floor. She must have been near sixty years of age at that time, as she had married late, but his father had laughed – all three of them had laughed, heartily, and had kept on laughing while she picked the pancakes and the pieces of the broken plate up, off the floor. (p.41)
Quote
If a part of Cathal now wondered how he might have turned out if his father had been another type of man and had not laughed, Cathal did not let his mind dwell on it. He told himself it meant little, that it was just a bad joke. (p.42)
]]></description><link>universidad/literature-ii/so-late-in-the-day.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/So Late in the Day.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 14:25:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>universidad/literature-ii/sentence-balance.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/Sentence Balance.md</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>universidad/literature-ii/sentence-structures.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/Sentence Structures.md</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>universidad/literature-ii/reflective-essay-250-w..html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/Reflective Essay 250 w..md</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>universidad/literature-ii/resource-kit-writing-the-reflective-literary-essay.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/Resource Kit - Writing the Reflective Literary Essay.md</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[So late in the day Reflection]]></title><description><![CDATA[When I was reading ]]></description><link>universidad/literature-ii/so-late-in-the-day-reflection.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Literature II/So late in the day Reflection.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 01:34:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cognitive Grammar]]></title><link>universidad/adquisición/cognitive-grammar.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/Adquisición/Cognitive Grammar.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 13:08:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[No title]]></title><link>universidad/pe-3/ellis-error-mistakes-(1997).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/PE 3/Ellis Error mistakes (1997).md</guid></item><item><title><![CDATA[Untitled]]></title><description><![CDATA[No se encontró “Ellis Error mistakes (1997) (1).pdf”.]]></description><link>universidad/pe-3/untitled.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/PE 3/Untitled.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 01:44:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rubrica - Secuencia Didáctica PE 3]]></title><description><![CDATA[
Encabezado (escuela, curso, horario, docente mentor, año y nivel)
Descripción del grupo de estudiantes (usando categorías teóricas)
Objetivos
Metas (Goals)
Tema (Topic)
Tarea (Task)
Contenidos lingüísticos (Language content)
Habilidades (Skills)
Número de clases y semanas estimadas
Materiales (textos, videos y otros recursos)
Actividades y justificaciones por etapa (2 a 4 por etapa) La tarea se articula con los objetivos, metas, contenidos lingüísticos y habilidades
Los materiales están en coherencia con los objetivos, metas, contenidos y habilidades
Se integran contenidos del CSE (Currículo Secundario Específico)
Las actividades son adecuadas para cada etapa y están justificadas con argumentos sólidos
Las actividades se articulan con los objetivos y metas El archivo está nombrado como: Apellido_2nd_MidTerm2023
Formato PDF
Fuente: Times New Roman 12
Interlineado 1.5
El archivo fue entregado en Moodle bajo “Practice papers &amp; Midterms”
Entregado antes del 1 de agosto a las 00:00 pm
]]></description><link>universidad/pe-3/rubrica-secuencia-didáctica-pe-3.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Universidad/PE 3/Rubrica - Secuencia Didáctica PE 3.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2025 19:10:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Monstruo(s)]]></title><description><![CDATA[Llegan al Lucio Molas y por lo que saben la morgue se encuentra en uno de los pisos inferiores pero no saben exactamente dónde ya que no es un lugar que un lugar que frecuenten a menos que sean forenses o que sus cuerpos mortales lleguen a ese lugar.Irrumpir con una tirada de Astucia + Hurto (Dificultad 3)]]></description><link>vampiro/monstruo(s).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Vampiro/Monstruo(s).md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jul 2025 04:18:13 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>